<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Medicina statica, or, Rules of health in eight sections of aphorisms / originally written by Sanctorius ... ; English'd by J.D.</title>
            <author>Santorio, Santorio, 1561-1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 98 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34215</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14147755</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14147755</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61662)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1069:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Medicina statica, or, Rules of health in eight sections of aphorisms / originally written by Sanctorius ... ; English'd by J.D.</title>
                  <author>Santorio, Santorio, 1561-1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 180 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Starkey ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXVI [1676]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hygiene --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicina Statica:</hi> OR, RULES OF Health, In Eight Sections OF APHORISMS. Originally written by <hi>Sanctorius</hi> Chief Profeſſor of Phyſick at <hi>Padua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Engliſh'd by <hi>J. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Starkey,</hi> at the <hi>Miter</hi> in
<hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> MDCLXXVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Weighing Chair</head>
                  <figDesc>a man sitting in a chair on a pulley system, with a meal on a table in front of him</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 23. 1676.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:3"/>
            <head>TO THE Much Honour'd, <hi>W. Witherings</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE grand Concern, in order to felicity in the <hi>next World,</hi> is that of true
<hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> in order to happineſs in <hi>this,</hi> that of our health. How induſtriouſly and tenderly we ought to demean our ſelves for the attaining of the former, and preſerving of the latter, the elaborate Works of <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors,</hi> on the one ſide, and <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> on the other, are a ſufficient teſtimony.</p>
            <p>Among the latter, our Author, <hi>Sanctorius,</hi> chief Profeſſor of Phyſick, in his time, at <hi>Padua,</hi> hath been very eminent for his many Productions upon that Subject; but more particularly by this, wherein he entertains us with a new diſcovery; but ſuch as he had found confirmable by above thirty years ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, as to the preſent publication of it in the Engliſh Tongue, ſo long after its firſt appearance in the Original, I have only to ſay, that you were in ſome meaſure the
<pb facs="tcp:102101:4"/>occaſion of it. For, though I had had the Traduction by me ſome conſiderable time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; Yet I ſhould have ſuffer'd it to have lain by a while longer, if ſome accidental diſcourſe concerning it, had not awakened my thoughts into a change of that Reſolution. And that encourag'd me to this Dedication, with this deſire only, that it may ſtand as a publick acknowledgement of the ſatisfaction and advantages, which I have derived from your happy ucquaintance, and conſequently how much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Worthy Sir,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>J. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:4"/>
            <head>Sanctorius TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT is a thing new, and not before heard of, in Medicine, that any one ſhould be able to find out the exact weight of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible perſpiration, nor has any one of the Philoſophers or Phyſicians attempted the doing of any thing in that part of the Medical Faculty. I am the firſt that has eſſay'd it, and (if I am not miſtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en) brought the Art to perfection, by reaſon, and the experience of thirty years. I have thought it fitter to deliver it in an
<hi>Aphoriſtical,</hi> than a <hi>Diexodical</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, for ſeveral reaſons: as firſt, that ſo I might imitate our great Dictator, whoſe ſteps I have always thought it an
<pb facs="tcp:102101:5"/>honour to follow. Secondly, I was in a manner neceſſitated to do ſo, in regard that the experiments themſelves, wherein I had ſpent many years, did naturally ſo lead me to this <hi>Aphoriſtical</hi> way of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as that I have digeſted the <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms,</hi> excellently well connected amongſt themſelves, in this wonderful order, as Bees having firſt gather'd the Hony from a great variety of flowers, do afterwards in an excellent order and aeconomy diſpoſe it wrought up to perfection into the little receptacles of their hony-combs.</p>
            <p>As to the Advantages of the Art, I ſhall ſay nothing, ſince it is known to all, of how great concern in the medical faculty, the knowledge of inſenſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration is. Only I would have the kind Reader take this one Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſince the ſtate of humane af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs is ſuch that men are more apt envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to oppoſe, than ſtudiouſly to promote the advancement of new deſigns, I know that many, not only among the vulgar, but alſo among the learned, not conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a love of the Truth, but hurried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb facs="tcp:102101:5"/>by ambition, or the vain letchery of contradiction, or pure envy, will riſe up againſt this new Art, and will heavily inveigh againſt it, though they are not ſo much as acquainted with the very name of it. But, if they are deſirous to be followers of the truth, I ſhall ſo far ſatisfy them all, as that they ſhall not only apprehend the pure refined truth in their minds and underſtandings, but they ſhall ſee it with their Eies, and feel it with their Hands, if they ſhall but ſtrictly examine, by the Ballance, all thoſe things which I have delivered in this Book, concerning the ponderation of inſenſible Perſpiration, its cauſes, time, advantages and diſadvantages, exceſs and defect, as alſo of the Air, meats, drinks, and the other ſix non-natural things, by which perſpiration is obſtructed, or advanc'd.</p>
            <p>Let them not therefore with a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilious arrogance make a light account of this Ballance, or, like ſmatterers in knowledge, calumniate this moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Art, inaſmuch as I ſhall not think
<pb facs="tcp:102101:6"/>they deſerve any other anſwer, than that ſmart raillery of the Poet
<hi>Perſius;</hi> when blinding themſelves like the <hi>Andabatae,</hi> and being obſtinate Truth-haters, they diſcover to all the world, that they are not only dull <hi>Euboeans</hi> and
<hi>Cordubans,</hi> in the perception of the Truth, but alſo moſt frivolous
<hi>Ariſtarchus</hi>'s and Criticks, in their cenſures of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:6"/>
            <head>An Account of the Weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chair.</head>
            <p>THE Aphoriſms compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in our Book of <hi>Statick Medicine,</hi> publiſh'd ſome years ſince, are found to be true, by the uſe of the Chair, plac'd at the Frontiſpiece.</p>
            <p>From which Chair we gain two advantages; the former, by finding out the daily inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible perſpiration of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; which perſpiration not well conſider'd, Medicine proves for the the moſt part vain and ineffectual: for all indiſpoſitions almoſt are the productions of a leſſer, or larger, perſpiration than is requiſite.</p>
            <p>The latter, in that, having ſeated our ſelves in this Chair,
<pb facs="tcp:102101:7"/>we perceive, during our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, when we are come to that juſt proportion of meat, and drink, beyond which, or ſhort of which, we are prejudic'd.</p>
            <p>The Chair is ſet as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the aforeſaid Figure wherein the Beam is faſtned to the Rafters, at a ſecret place, in a room above that where you take refection, becauſe it would be ſomewhat unſightly in the ſame Room; as alſo by reaſon of the unlearned, to whom all things that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual ſeem ridiculous. Now the Chair, being a fingers breadth diſtant from the Floor, ſtands firm, ſo as that it cannot eaſily be ſhaken.</p>
            <p>When therefore, by reaſon of the refection we have taken, we are come to the juſt weight and meaſure before preſcribed,
<pb facs="tcp:102101:7"/>then the remote part of the Beam is a little elevated, and the Chair withal immediately deſcends a little. That deſcent of the Chair tells the perſon ſitting in it, that he has taken the requiſite quantity of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>Now what quantity or weight of wholeſome meats is convenient for every one, and how much the inſenſible perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ought to be in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective bodies, to wit, that perſpiration which is commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly weigh'd by the Chair, any one may eaſily underſtand by our Book of <hi>Statick Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:102101:8"/>
            <head>THE SECTIONS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>OF the Ponderation of inſenſible Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Of Air and Waters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Of Meat and Drink.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Of Sleep and Vigilance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Of Exerciſe and Reſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>Of Venery.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>Of the Affections of the Mind.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>An Anſwer to the Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comaſtix.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102101:8"/>
            <hi>Rules of Health.</hi>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <head>The Firſt Section.</head>
            <head> OF Inſenſible Perſpiration, AND THE EXACT WEIGHT thereof.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>Aphoriſm I.</head>
                  <p>IF the addition of thoſe things that are deficient, and the ſubſtraction of thoſe that are exuberant, be daily made, as to quantity and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102101:9"/>ſuch as it ought to be, loſt health would be recover'd, and the preſent always preſerv'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>If the Phyſician, who has the overſight of other mens Health, be capable of judging only of the ſenſible addition, and evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and knows not the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of their daily inſenſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, he does not cure, but deceive them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>He only who knows, to what quantity, and when, the ſecret perſpiration of a man's body a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to more or leſs, ſhall find out how much, and when, any thing ought to be added, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, in order to the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or recovery of his Health.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Inſenſible perſpiration alone is commonly wont to exceed all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102101:9"/>the ſenſible perſpirations put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Inſenſible perſpiration is made either by the pores of the body, which is tranſpirable in all its parts, and is enclos'd in the Skin as it were in a net; or by reſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, perform'd by the Mouth, which in one day commonly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to about half a pound: for that may be diſcover'd by the dewey drops upon a Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſs, if it be ſet cloſe to the Mouth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>If the meat and drink taken in one day amount to the weight of eight pounds, the inſenſible tranſpiration ordinarily amounts to five pounds, or thereabouts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>The quantity of inſenſible tranſpiration admits of ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102101:10"/>variety according to the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Nature, Climate, Seaſons, Age, Diſeaſes, Aliment, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things that are non-natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>It may be eaſily computed what was the quantity of the nocturnal perſpiration, and that of the ſenſible excrements, by weighing the body in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, before and after ſenſible excretion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>If the weight of the body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be augmented more than it is wont, without any greater addition of meat and drink, or a retention of the ſenſible excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, there enſues a difficulty of breathing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>The Body is preſerv'd in the ſame ſtate of Health, when it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102101:10"/>to the ſame weight, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any unuſual ſenſible evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: But if it be reduc'd to the ſame weight, by a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary evacuation, by Urine, or Stoole, it begins to receed from its former Health.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>If it be perceiv'd by pondera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that there hath been any obſtruction of the perſpiration, there will ſucceed in the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent days, either a more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful perſpiration, or ſome more abundant ſenſible evacuation, or ſome ſymptom of an evil habit of the body, or a Feaver.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>Much perſpiration, and a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and more than uſual ſenſible evacuation are not conſiſtent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>If any one does ſenſibly eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102101:11"/>more than is requiſite, his perſpiration is leſs than is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>It is an ill ſign, when a man goes to Stool, Urines, or Sweats, more than is requiſite, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires leſs than he ſhould do.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>If the body be dayly reduc'd to the ſame weight, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny alteration in the evacuation of thoſe things that are perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it will need no criſis, and will be continu'd in a ſound poſture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>When the body is one day of one weight, and another day of another, it argues an introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of evil qualities into it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>That weight, which to any one is ſuch, as that, when he goes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102101:11"/>up ſome ſteepy place, he feels himſelf lighter than he is wont, is the exact ſtandard of good Health.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>Evil qualities are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of exceſs, but we muſt not affirm the contrary, to wit, that good qualities are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of defect.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>Not only the weight, but the exceſs alſo is diminiſh'd, either by the evacuation of the ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or inſenſible crude matter, or by that of the ſenſible or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible concocted matter. The latter conduces to health, the former takes away the exceſs, but leaves the ill quality behind.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>There are two kinds of inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible tranſpiration; the one is immediately made after ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102101:12"/>upon the compleating of the concoction, and after this there is an augmentation of a man's ſtrength; the other, in the time of vigilance; and this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is occaſion'd by crude hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and by reaſon thereof the ſtrength is impair'd. For it is performed with more or leſs vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, anſwerably to the greater or leſs motion of the vigilance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>That perſpiration which eaſes the body of a great and that an unprofitale burthen, is not that which is attended with Sweating, but that inviſible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration or breathing, ſuch as is that, which in the ſpace of Four and Twenty hours, in the winter time, may exhale Fifty Ounces, or more.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>Inviſible perſpiration becomes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102101:12"/>viſible, either when there is an exceſs of nutriment, or when there is a remiſſion of Heat, or by reaſon of violent motion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>Inſenſible perſpiration attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Sweating is not good; becauſe ſweating abates the ſtrength of the fibres. Yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is accounted good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it occaſions a diverſion from a greater evil.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>The more ſubtile and free from moiſture the inviſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration is; the more Healthy it is.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>All the liquid excrements are the more weighty, and fall down to the bottom: the thick are lighter, and keep up on the top, ſuch as are hard and thick Dregs, Spittles, and others of that kind.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102101:13"/>
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>Liquid excrements, allowing an equality as to quantity, take off a greater burthen from the body, than the hard and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>Liquid meats are alſo the more weighty, and the ſolid the more light; Bread and Fleſh are light; Wine and Broaths are heavy. A Cup of Wine is of equivalent weight to a piece of Bread though above thrice as big as it in bulk.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>When the Body ſeems to be more burthenſome to a man, when it is not really ſo, he is in a worſe condition, than if it ſeem and is felt to be ſuch, when it is really ſuch.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>The weight of an Animal may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102101:13"/>be conſider'd two ways; for theſe two things are conſiſtent, to wit, that the body may be more weighty than uſual, and yet the perſon fancie himſelf lighter; and on the contrary, that the body may be lighter than uſual, yet the party feel himſelf heavier.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>If theſe two things concurre, to wit, that a man feel himſelf lighter than he is, and yet is not really ſo, it is an argument of a moſt healthful conſtitution.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>That body which is reduc'd to a leſs weight, than is proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable to the juſt computation of its healthful ſtate, is in a worſe condition, than that, which acquires a greater weight than is proportionable to its Healthfulneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102101:14"/>
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>When the body, by reaſon of any exerciſe of it ſelf, or of the mind, becomes of leſs weight, there immediately enſues a dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of its vigour; which does not happen, if it becomes of leſs weight after ſleep, when there is a perfect concoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>If without any precedent vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence there be a diminution of the weight, and an impairing of the vigour; the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is not ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd, as had been loſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>There are but three ways, whereby an Animal is weakned, either while the weight of the body is augmented, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impairing of its vigour; when the vigour is diminiſh'd, the ſame weight of the body ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102101:14"/>or laſtly, when both vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, and weight admit of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>That wearineſs which enſues upon the Body's becoming leſs ſtrong, and of leſs weight, is more dangerous than any other: for ponderoſity is a kind of ſtrength.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>The weight of the body com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates ſtrength to us, when we either draw any thing down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, or carry, turn, or thruſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVII.</head>
                  <p>The ſtrength of an old man does many times depend more on the weight, than the vigour of his body: an old Animal of little weight may live a long time, but cannot be ſtrong.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102101:15"/>
                  <head>XXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>If after ſleeping the body be reduc'd to its uſual weight, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feeling any trouble,
'tis well; for it argu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perfect concoction; but if with trouble, 'tis ill.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIX.</head>
                  <p>The body does not fall into any diſeaſe upon external miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, unleſs it have ſome of the entrails prepar'd for it: that preparation is diſcover'd by the more or leſs than uſual weight, occaſion'd not without ſome precedent diſturbance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XL.</head>
                  <p>If nature be obſtructed while ſhe is employ'd in the office of perſpiration, ſhe becomes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently defective in divers others.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLI.</head>
                  <p>When the head akes, the body receives a ſudden check in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, and becomes more ponderous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102101:15"/>
                  <head>XLII.</head>
                  <p>The firſt ſeeds of diſeaſes are more certainly diſcover'd by the alteration of the unuſual perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, than by the obſtruction of the offices.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIII.</head>
                  <p>If by ponderation thou ſhalt find that the matter of uſual per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration is retain'd in the body, and that the party does neither ſweat nor urine for ſome days after, infer thence that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd matter prognoſticates fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture corruption.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIV.</head>
                  <p>But if by ponderation thou ſhalt find, that, upon ſome vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent cauſe, the perſpirable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is more than uſually emitted out of the body, be aſſur'd, that the place where the perſpirable matters had been lodg'd, and whence they were violently eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102101:16"/>is fill'd with crudities, which are crowded into the ſmalleſt paſſages.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLV.</head>
                  <p>Yet if thoſe crudities which ſo force their way in, could, as to all parts, be rendred fluid and perſpirable, 'twere well; but if not, the part wherein they are contain'd firſt becomes hard, like Leather, and at laſt ſchirrous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVI.</head>
                  <p>If that which is perſpirable ſhould not be diſſipated either by nature, or ſome feaveriſh heat, the body would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately prepar'd for a malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Feaver.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVII.</head>
                  <p>Such as are in Feavers are as likely to grow worſe and worſe, if their perſpiration be diverted by the exceſſive applications of Medicines from an unskilful
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102101:16"/>Phyſician, as it might be if di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by the miſcarriages of the patients themſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVIII.</head>
                  <p>A ſmall quantity of <hi>Caſſia</hi> does not divert perſpiration, does not impair the ſtrength, but only eaſes the body of a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous weight: but other Medicines contribute more to evacuation, are diffus'd to the more remote parts, and render the body lighter; and yet the Meat and Drink, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd afterwards, fill up the eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated paſſages, thence the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and bladder are exſicatted, and ſoon after the body com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly becomes more ponder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIX.</head>
                  <p>Any Pain, or Grief of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, obſtructs the paſſage of that perſpirable matter which is concocted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102101:17"/>
                  <head>L.</head>
                  <p>Any cold, even the leaſt, that we feel in the night while we are aſleep, obſtructs perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LI.</head>
                  <p>One of the moſt frequent cauſes that hinder perſpiration, in the Summer time, is the often turning of our bodies in bed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LII.</head>
                  <p>There are three internal cauſes of the obſtruction of perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Nature's being otherwiſe employ'd, diverſion, and want of ſtrength.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIII.</head>
                  <p>Hence it appears by a ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ponderation, that on the day a man takes Phyſick, and dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpace of three hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter refection, there is little per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration: for on ſuch day of taking Phyſick Nature is buſied about ſenſible evacuation; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102101:17"/>after meat ſhe is intent on the firſt concoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIV.</head>
                  <p>In Fluxes, and Vomiting, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration is obſtructed, becauſe it is diverted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LV.</head>
                  <p>A burthenſome weight of Garments is a hindrance to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, becauſe they abate a man's ſtrength.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVI.</head>
                  <p>The body does not perſpire every hour after the ſame rate, in regard that after refection, in the ſpace of five hours, it is commonly wont to exhale a pound or thereabouts; from the fifth hour to the twelfth, about three Pound; from the twelfth to the ſixteenth (at which time we are to take refection, or Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick) hardly half a pound.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102101:18"/>
                  <head>LVII.</head>
                  <p>He who takes his refection, or is evacuated by Phyſick, dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hours of greateſt perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; ſuch as are, for the moſt part, thoſe of the morning, is highly injur'd; becauſe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after meat, as alſo after Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, perſpiration is extreamly diverted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVIII.</head>
                  <p>The ſecret and inſenſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration eaſes us more than all the ſenſible ones put together: for, after ſleep, before there be any evacuation of the ſenſible excrements, every one feels him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf lighter, becauſe he is really become lighter, by three pound or thereabouts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIX.</head>
                  <p>In the ſpace of one night, there are commonly evacuated, of Urine, ſixteen Ounces, more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102101:18"/>or leſs; of concocted excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by ſtool, four Ounces; and by occult perſpiration, forty and above.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LX.</head>
                  <p>There are many who in the ſpace of four and twenty hours evacuate as much by inſenſible perſpiration as they do by ſtool in the ſpace of fifteen daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXI.</head>
                  <p>How comes it then, that moſt of our Country-men, in all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes, mind only the evacuation by Stool or Urine, and hardly ever think of inſenſible perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXII.</head>
                  <p>If in the night thou haſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd more than uſually, but without Sweating or any diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, be aſſur'd of thy being in perfect Health.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102101:19"/>
                  <head>LXIII.</head>
                  <p>Then are we at the greateſt diſtance from any diſeaſe, when we are come to the mean propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the latitude of healthy ponderation, not through ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous ſenſible evacuation, or that preſcrib'd by the Phyſician, or yet by faſting, but by the inſenſible perſpiration, which comes by ſleep, after perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXIV.</head>
                  <p>What quantity of perſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is convenient for every one, in order to his continuance in a moſt healthful conſtitution of body, you will thus find out. Obſerve in the morning, after a ſomewhat-plentiful Supper o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver night, that ſort of greater per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, which may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated in thy ſelf in the ſpace of Twelve Hours: grant it to have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102101:19"/>amounted to Fifty Ounces: ſome other morning, after faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over-night, yet with this proviſo, that thou didſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed at thy Dinner the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, make the ſame obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; let us admit the perſpiration to have amounted to Twenty Ounces: This fore-known, pitch upon that moderate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Meat and other non-natural cauſes, which will be likely to reduce thee daily to the mean between Fifty and Twenty Ounces; and that mean will be Thirty Five Ounces. Thus maiſt thou live a long and healthful life, nay haply arrive to that of a hundred years.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXV.</head>
                  <p>The healthful bodies of men, and ſuch as are moſt moderate in their diet, become every month more than uſually ponderous, to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102101:20"/>wit, by one pound or two, and are reduc'd to the uſual weight about the month's end, as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to Women, but after a cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis made by a more plentiful or more muddy emiſſion of Urne,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXVI.</head>
                  <p>Before the ſaid menſtrual cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis made ſoon after ſleep, either there is felt a drowſineſs of the head, or wearineſs of the body; and afterwards, by a more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Evacuation of Urine, all things are quieted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXVII.</head>
                  <p>The external cauſes which ordinarily obſtruct perſpiration are a cold, troubled, and moiſt air; ſwimming in cold water, groſs, and viſcous meats; the intermiſſion of Corporeal exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, or that of the mind, and, in robuſt perſons, over much abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from venery.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102101:20"/>
                  <head>LXVIII.</head>
                  <p>External cold obſtructs Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration in a weak body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its heat is diſſipated; but in a robuſt perſon, it augments it: for the heat is forc'd to the bottom, and reduplicated, and thereupon nature is corrobora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and upon that the weight of the perſpirable matter that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd being by her conſum'd, the body becomes, and is felt lighter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXIX.</head>
                  <p>The health of that body is more firm and of longer continuance, whoſe weight in the proceſs of many years is neither augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor diminiſh'd, than that of a body whoſe weight is alter'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very year.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXX.</head>
                  <p>For a body to be reduc'd to its uſual ponderoſity, by the acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102101:21"/>of crude humours, is ill; but if it be by the addition of ſuch as are concocted, it is moſt wholſome.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXI.</head>
                  <p>It is an ill ſign, when a healthy perſon becomes of leſs weight than uſual, it being ſuppos'd his courſe of life be the ſame as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: for there is not any refuſion of that wholſome matter which had been loſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXII.</head>
                  <p>The concocted excrements of the belly are of great bulk, but little weight; they ſwim on the ſurface, by reaſon of the air con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in them, and whatever may be evacuated, at one and the ſame time, never exceeds the third part of a pound.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="73" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXIII.</head>
                  <p>If it happen that in one dayes ſpace, through ſome miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102101:21"/>or other, there be ſo great a retention of perſpiration as may amount to a pound, nature is commonly three days employ'd in the inſenſible expurgation of that which had been retain'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="74" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXIV.</head>
                  <p>Then does nature make a great inſenſible evacuation, when ſhe endeavours to voyd perſpirable matter retain'd, by yawnings and extenſions of the joynts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="75" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXV.</head>
                  <p>The perſpirable matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of two parts, to wit, a light, and a ponderous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="76" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXVI.</head>
                  <p>The ponderous part is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uberant that living creatures are generated of it, as Punaizes, lice, and the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="77" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXVII.</head>
                  <p>From the more ponderous part of perſpiration do proceed the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102101:22"/>contagious Infections of ſuch as lye together: for the light part vaniſhes, but the more ponder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, being adheſive, does infect.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="78" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>They who in the ſcorching Heats of Summer are obſtructed in the exhalation of the perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable matter, are incommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Heat; but to thoſe who have an abſolute freedom of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, the Heat is not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="79" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXIX.</head>
                  <p>A greater weight differs from a leſſer equal healthful, becauſe the greater does the more acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate old Age. Be it ſuppos'd, that ſome perſon hath his Health as well when he weighs two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred weight, as at two hundred and five pound: we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd that the exceſs of thoſe five pounds did more accelerate old Age.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="80" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:102101:22"/>
                  <head>LXXX.</head>
                  <p>Why does Animated Fleſh live, and not putrify, as a carcaſe does? Becauſe it is daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd. Why are Children in a capacity of living longer than old men? Becauſe they may be more often renew'd, ſince they begin from the loweſt weight of the whole latitude, and ſo proceed to the higheſt: for they are capable of moſt of the Healthful weights. Why is there a neceſſity that old men ſhould die? Becauſe they are capable only of the laſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of weight. But why only of thoſe? becauſe their fibres are hard, and, as ſuch, cannot be any more renew'd; whence death enſues.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="81" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXI.</head>
                  <p>Why are they cur'd are who ſurpriz'd by ſome dangerous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe?
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102101:23"/>becauſe they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſeveral ſorts of Healthy weights: for ſuch Diſeaſes take away thirty pounds from mens bodies, more or leſs, as the bodies are more or leſs repleat, and as the Diſeaſe is more or leſs hot, and according to its continuance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>APHORISMS <hi>Added by the Author.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="82" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXII.</head>
                  <p>Old men prolong their lives by frequent Spittings; for theſe being retain'd within the body, as being uncapable of coction or digeſtion, hinder perſpiration; the conſequences whereof are ſuffocation and death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="83" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102101:23"/>
                  <head>LXXXIII.</head>
                  <p>Old Age is indeed a Diſeaſe, but may laſt a long time, if the body be made eaſily perſpirable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="84" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXIV.</head>
                  <p>Venery, actual frigidity of the body, over-plentiful drinking, ſupping as young men do, to be angry more than needs, and much exerciſe; all theſe ſhorten the lives of old men.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="85" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXV.</head>
                  <p>Old men reach not decrepit Age by reaſon of the weakneſs of their expulſive faculties. Thence it comes to paſs; that when they drink more than it was requiſite they ſhould, they urine leſs, and perſpire leſs than they are wont. The remedy is, that the ſubſtraction be equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to the addition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="86" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXVI.</head>
                  <p>Inſenſible perſpiration being
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102101:24"/>quite obſtructed, does not only deprive the chiefeſt parts of life, but alſo one ignoble part. It deprives the chiefeſt, when there is an Apoplexy in the Brain; pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation in the Heart, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Blood in the Liver; and a ſuffocation in the Matrix; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives the ignoble part by Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="87" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXVII.</head>
                  <p>That Women are troubled with the ſuffocation does not proceed from the Womb's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the midriff, but from the frigidity of the corrupted ſeed, which does not want per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="88" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>The humours of perſons trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the Gout, though they are moſt groſs, are diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved only by way of vapour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="89" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102101:24"/>
                  <head>LXXXIX.</head>
                  <p>Vomiting diverts Urine and perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="90" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XC.</head>
                  <p>The frequent turning of the body in bed, ſince the doing of it requires the aſſiſtance of all the muſcles, does weaken, and obſtruct concoction and perſpiration. The remedy is, for one to be obſtinately reſolv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d to lye in one and the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="91" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCI.</head>
                  <p>While the knees are kept actually warm the feet are not chil'd; ſuch perſons ſleep well, they perſpire more, and urine leſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="92" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCII.</head>
                  <p>Looſeneſs of the belly is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by thoſe things which augment perſpiration, of which kind Bathing is one.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="93" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:102101:25"/>
                  <head>XCIII.</head>
                  <p>As the Loadſtone is better pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerv'd where there is much iron; and wine, better kept in a great veſſel, than a litle one: So ſuch bodies as are more ponderous, yet healthy withal, do better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſtrength, than ſuch as abate in their weight, through want of aliment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="94" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCIV.</head>
                  <p>They who urine more than they drink, do perſpire little, or nothing at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="95" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCV.</head>
                  <p>Why is there an obſtruction of inſenſible perſpiration in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termittent Feavers? becauſe the peccant humour is in the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="96" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCVI.</head>
                  <p>In the Dropſy, the water in the lower part of the belly is not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, becauſe its drought and hardneſs hinder perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="97" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:102101:25"/>
                  <head>XCVII.</head>
                  <p>Hot humours being got toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into any part are to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd with hot digeſtives, in order to their diſſolution by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="98" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCVIII.</head>
                  <p>Why is fainting or ſwouning beneficial in high Feavers? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cauſes ſweating and a ſtrong perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="99" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCIX.</head>
                  <p>If the pricking of a nerve be clos'd up with Milk, Meal, or any ſuch thing, the retain'd ichor becomes ſo ſharp and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roding, that the Patients die of Convulſions, if the wound be not opened with Oyl.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="100" type="aphorism">
                  <head>C.</head>
                  <p>Perſpiration is beneficial in tumours, if it be procur'd by things actually and potentially moiſt; otherwiſe they turn to a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102101:26"/>ſcirrhus, by diſſolving the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuious humour, and leaving the groſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="101" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CI.</head>
                  <p>If any part of the body be full of blood, or ſome other humour, as it is obſerv'd in tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and in the pleuriſy it ſelf, it is not to be refrigerated; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the matter being evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, it is refrigerated of it ſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="102" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CII.</head>
                  <p>Hypochondriacal perſons are recover'd of their Diſtemper, if their bodies be made perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by frequent Bathings, and be kept to moiſt diet.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="103" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CIII.</head>
                  <p>Inſenſible perſpiration pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd by fomentations, in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purged body, attracts more hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours than it diſſolves; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in <hi>Simon</hi>'s caſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="104" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:102101:26"/>
                  <head>CIV.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe bodies which inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly perſpire much are neither purg'd nor blooded, as it is manifeſt in Children.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="105" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CV.</head>
                  <p>How come Lice to be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated? Becauſe the perſpiration of the malignant ichor, or thin matter, is obſtructed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="106" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CVI.</head>
                  <p>A Gangrene is prevented by thoſe things that promote per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration; by thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote ſuppuration, it becomes a ſphacelus, that is, when any part is mortify'd by inflammation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="107" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CVII.</head>
                  <p>Why does the part affected with a Gangrene die? Becauſe the little arteries, by reaſon of the redundancy of blood, are not rais'd up. 'Tis remedied by ſenſible and inſenſible perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="108" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:102101:27"/>
                  <head>CVIII.</head>
                  <p>The moſt clammy humours in robuſt bodies make their way out through the narroweſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, as it is manifeſt by the Fatneſs voided by Urine, as alſo by a mixture of Water and Hony injected into a wounded breaſt; and conſequently they muſt make their way through the inſenſible paſſages.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="109" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CIX.</head>
                  <p>By difflation, as well the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial as the ſuperfluous matter is evacuated; but if after ſleep ſtrength and vigour be acquir'd, the ſuperfluous matter only is for the moſt part evacuated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="110" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CX.</head>
                  <p>That difflation which is not ſenſibly perceiv'd is natural, and is an argument of ſtrength; but ſweating argues the contrary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="111" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:102101:27"/>
                  <head>CXI.</head>
                  <p>If in the winter time any part of the body be very cold, the whole does ſo far ſympathize with it, that the concoction and perſpiration of the whole is thereby leſſen'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="112" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXII.</head>
                  <p>Swimming is more ſafe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the evening: in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the pores are ſtopped by the coldneſs of the water, whence there is ſome danger of a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="113" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXIII.</head>
                  <p>If in the Summer time the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ly uncover'd, the perſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is obſtructed; whereupon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue a drowſineſs and heavineſs of the Head, and a bruiſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weildineſs of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="114" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXIV.</head>
                  <p>If the weight of the body be augmented in the ſpace of five
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102101:28"/>or ſix daies, it is not to be tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en off of a ſudden, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees: for abſtinence from food, if it be extraordinary, hurts the Stomach, the Brain, and the Heart, and after a while, the whole body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="115" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXV.</head>
                  <p>In Autumn, the weight of the body is augmented; which if it exceed the ſtandard of the Healthy latitude, Tertians, and other putrid Feavers, are apt to be the conſequences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="116" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXVI.</head>
                  <p>Things that are extream cold in a violent Feaver, if they be not heated, prove mortal, by reaſon of the difficulty of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="117" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXVII.</head>
                  <p>Nothing is more hurtful to malignant Ulcers, than thoſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102101:28"/>things that hinder perſpiration, as fatneſs, oyl, wax.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="118" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXVIII.</head>
                  <p>Of all the intermittent Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, the Quotidian only is not without danger; for Flegm is one of the chiefeſt things that obſtruct perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="119" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXIX.</head>
                  <p>If the perſpiration be ſtop'd in the neck, the ſenſe of the pericranium is ſtupify'd, as may be obſerv'd in perſons walking in the wind and rain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="120" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXX.</head>
                  <p>Nothing is more apt to take away putrefaction, than for one to uſe much Ventilation, not only that which is procur'd by what is drawn in, but alſo by what is evacuated through the inſenſible paſſages.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="121" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXI.</head>
                  <p>Refrigerations in acute diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102101:29"/>are ſymptoms of death, as in <hi>Hermocrates:</hi> for they take away perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="122" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXII.</head>
                  <p>After bathing, the pores of the skin ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> condens'd with oyl, to the end that, the alimental moiſture being
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ttracted may not be diſſolved. In dangerous caſes therefore, uſe oyl to cloſe and not to open the pores.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="123" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXIII.</head>
                  <p>And yet that courſe of diet, which we leaſt regard, brings us to an old age great as that of
<hi>Philip.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="124" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXIV.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Diaphragma,</hi> or Midriff by contracting it ſelf to its prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, dilates the breaſt; by that dilatation, is inſpiration wrought. And by dilating it ſelf, it contracts the breaſt, and by that contraction expiration is wrought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="125" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:102101:29"/>
                  <head>CXXV.</head>
                  <p>But the <hi>Spincter,</hi> or the Muſcle that ſhuts the bladder, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting it ſelf to its principle cloſes the bladder, and keeps in the Urine; by ſpreading it ſelf, it dilates the bladder, and emits the urine.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Peſtilence.</head>
               <div n="126" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXVI.</head>
                  <p>THings infected with the plague, communicate the infection, as long as the next and remote cauſes remain; but any one of thoſe failing, the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ceaſes, like the motion of a clock, when, upon the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Tooth in any one Wheel, it is at a ſtand.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="127" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:102101:30"/>
                  <head>CXXVII.</head>
                  <p>We are not infected with the Plague by contact, but by drawing in the peſtiferous Air, or the vapours ariſing from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected goods. It happens thus: the vital ſpirit is infected by the Air, by ſuch infection of the ſpirit the blood is congeal'd, which laſt being fore'd outwards raiſes carbuncles, black ſpots, and Buboes: if it remain within, it cauſes death; if it be quite expell'd, we are paſt all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="128" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>If the whole infection be fore'd out into Carbuncles and Buboes, 'tis a good ſign; if not,
'tis mortal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="129" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXIX.</head>
                  <p>We are not of our ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Plague, but it is brought to us by others. This
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102101:30"/>is manifeſt by the experiment of ſuch as are ſhut up in Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neries.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="130" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXX.</head>
                  <p>Not all, but much about the third part of mankind dies of the Peſtilence. That it is ſo, may be ſeen by the experiment of thoſe whoſe office it is to view the dead.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="131" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXXI.</head>
                  <p>They who conceive the blackneſs of the ſpots to be a ſign of aduſtion, are miſtaken; for many times aged men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing internally and externally cold, without any feaver, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this life in two days time, with the ſame blackneſs, but proceeding from a Thrombus, or clots of blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="132" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXXII.</head>
                  <p>If a ſmall quantity of blood, by reaſon of the vital ſpirit's
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102101:31"/>being infected, becomes a clot of blood, and this laſt be wholly thruſt out by buboes and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buncles, they are cur'd; if it be not wholly forc'd out, they die, as in the black ſpots.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="133" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXXIII.</head>
                  <p>Conſequent to this is it, that they, who have their ulcers and buboes open'd, if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal infection be wholly come out, recover; if not, they die.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="134" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXXIV.</head>
                  <p>There are two ways to put a ſtop to the plague; to wit, that the ſound be ſeparated, and that the infected may have place enough to air themſelves. There are two ways to do the latter; to wit, that they be not ſent to places they abhor to come into; and that their houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtuff be not burnt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="135" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:102101:31"/>
                  <head>CXXXV.</head>
                  <p>They whoſe lungs are thin, are eaſily infected with the Plague; the contrary is to be affirm'd of thoſe whoſe Lungs are thick. It argues the thinneſs of the Lungs, when any one drawing in his breath, as much as he can, that ſingle ſtroak of the Pulſe is ſomewhat weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or more gentle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="136" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXXVI.</head>
                  <p>The Plague is not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to fire, which increaſes upon the addition of fuel; but the former decreaſes, though the fuel of it remain in the ſame poſture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="137" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXXVII.</head>
                  <p>The raies of the Plague are remov'd from one place to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the wind; but not by any violence of a lucid body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="137" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:102101:32"/>
                  <head>CXXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>They who preſcribe any other remedy for the ſhunning of the Plague, beſides that of flying from it, are either ignorant men, or cheating Quacks.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="138" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXXXIX.</head>
                  <p>Hence it comes to paſs, that perſons of Quality none al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt are cur'd by remedies; but very many of the meaner ſort of people, without them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="139" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CXL.</head>
                  <p>Why does the Plague con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long? Becauſe, while it rages, they air things that are infected; which, while they are cleaning, Thieves ſteal and ſcatter up and down; after the Plague is at a ſtand, they do not infect, otherwiſe the Plague would be perpetual.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe ſome among the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102101:32"/>perſons, when they are forc'd out of the City, do not air themſelves as they ſhould do; by which means the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection increaſes.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe they do not prohibit the peoples aſſembling in Churches. Divine ſervice at ſuch times ſhould be perform'd in the open air.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe men make uſe of Chirurgeons that are ſtrangers, or forreigners, who are the better pleaſed, the greater the Plague is.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe they do not ſeparate the ſound into other houſes from the infected.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe they uſe internal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies againſt the Plague, when none can be adminiſtred, but what are hurtful.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe they permit poultry
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102101:33"/>to be brought to the market, which the ſound coming to handle, after they had been handled by the infected, are afterwards thereby infected.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:102101:33"/>
            <head>OF AIR <hi>and</hi> WATERS.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT.</hi> II.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>Aphoriſm I.</head>
                  <p>A Cold Air, and cold ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things put ſtrong bodies into a heat, and, by taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way what is ſuperfluous, make them lighter; but they refrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate weak bodies, and, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering the heat, make them more ponderous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Warm air, and buſhes actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warm, if crudities do not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102101:34"/>obſtruct, do alſo promote per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, refreſh the inward parts, and render mens bodies lighter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>An external air, penetrating into the innermoſt parts of the body, through the trunks of the arteries, may make the body more or leſs ponderous; leſs, if it be ſubtile, and warm; more, if it be thick, and moiſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>How great the ponderouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the air is, may in the firſt place, be gather'd from the greater or leſſer weight of the dregs of alom dried before in the Sun, and afterwards expos'd to the air in the night time. Secondly, from our feeling a greater cold than what is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in the weather-glaſs. For the moiſture or ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102101:34"/>of the air is to us the meaſure of its coldneſs. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the greater or leſſer bending of a very thin board, eſpecially if it be of Pear-tree. Fourthly, from the contraction of the ſtrings of a Lute, or from Hemp.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>How great the ponderouſneſs of water is, may eaſily be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, if ſome heavy thing be ſuppos'd appendent in the water. For that water is lighter, and conſequently the more wholſome, wherein the heavy thing does the more gravitate; but that wherein it does leſs gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate, is the more ponderous and the more unwholſome.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>That water which is more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and the Air that is more muddy, and more ponderous,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102101:35"/>convert the inviſible perſpiration into an ichor (or thin Matter) which being pent in, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards not diſſolv'd, does for the moſt part cauſe a cachexy, or evil diſpoſition of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>In a cold healthful Air perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is alſo obſtructed, the pores are condenſated; but the fibres are corroborated, and the weight of that perſpirable Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is retain'd neither hurts, nor is felt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>In a thick foggy air perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is obſtructed, the paſſages are fill'd, but not condens'd, the fibres are looſned, not ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd, and the weight of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable Matter unevacuated hurts, and is felt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>If cold weather ſucceed a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102101:35"/>warm Air, ſuch as that in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, it ſhall that day, it being ſuppos'd that a man takes the ſame liberty of drinking, hinder about a third part of the perſpiration, which, if it be not made ſenſible, is apt to diſpoſe the body to putrefaction, or ſome evil habit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>The hindrance of perſpiration occaſion'd by unexpected cold is more hurtful to work bodies, than that which is hindred by degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>He who is ſurpriz'd uncloath'd at ſuch time as a cool Air ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds a precedent heat, is wont to perſpire leſs by about two pounds in one days ſpace, yet without any ſenſible inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:102101:36"/>
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>A pleaſant and ſomewhat cool breeze is more prejudicial to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies well warmed, than the cold of Air and Water in an exceſſive degree: For the former does not render the body lighter, but obſtructs and looſens it; but the latter obſtructs and corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates it, and thence it comes that the bodies are leſs ponderous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>When the unwholſome qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of the Air and Water diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe bodies to a malignant pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction, their weight for the moſt part is but little heeded; as if this ſhould be the reaſon of it, that by their corruption the nerves become ſtronger, as it is obſerv'd in diſtracted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>To Swim in cold water after
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102101:36"/>violent exerciſe is extreamly pleaſant, but mortal: for there is nothing more pernicious than oppoſite motions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>That which treacherouſly diſpoſes the entrails to indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, does not many times ſeem to be either heavy, or unpleaſant.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>A pleaſant gale of wind from the ſouth ſurprizing a man at a violent exerciſe, is many times mortal; for the gale occaſions a difficulty of breathing, and from the exerciſe proceeds acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>It happens to thoſe, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſupper, are deſirous of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a cooler gale of wind than is requiſite, that the perſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that part which is not well cloath'd is obſtructed: but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102101:37"/>that night or the next day, moſt of them are ſubject to a great aking of the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>If bodies be ſuddenly ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of a warm air into a cool, they are injur'd; becauſe they are rendred of greater weight than is requiſite. If re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd out of a cold air into a warm, they are alſo endam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mag'd, becauſe they become leſs ſtrong.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>Perſons of weak conſtitutions make a greater converſion of the perſpirable matter retain'd, into Urine, in the winter time; robuſt perſons do the ſame in the ſummer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>Fanning obſtructs perſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and makes the head more ponderous, and more hot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:102101:37"/>
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>The wind, as it is colder than the skin, ſo is it ever obſtructive and hurtful to it, but more than any part to the head, becauſe it is moſt expos'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>In all ſeaſons of the year ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, dry weather is more healthy than continual rains, for it renders mens bodies lighter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>In the ſummer time, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate bodies are leſs ponderous, than they are in winter, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three pounds.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>In the ſummer time men are ſubject to wearineſs; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the body is more ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, but becauſe it is leſs ſtrong.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>In a warm air, the body is of leſs ſtrength, as well by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102101:38"/>that with the perſpiration there is ſomewhat of the better ſpirits exhal'd, as becauſe the warmth is not concentrated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>There is alwayes by a warm air ſomewhat diſperſed through the whole skin, which carries away with it ſomewhat of the internal good humour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>In the ſummer time we are troubled with heat, not prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally proceeding from the warmth of the air, for every part of the body is warmer than the ſummer-air, but becauſe there is not ſo much coldneſs in the ſummer-air, as that the natural heat may be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concentrated. Whence it comes to paſs, that, being ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd it cannot inſenſibly eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate that perſpirable matter
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102101:38"/>which is of its own nature hot: which matter being kept in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſharp, and is the cauſe of our being troubled with much heat.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>When mens bodies in the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſeaſons, upon ſleeping in the night or day time perſpire abundantly, or ſweat, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come lighter, and are not that day troubled with any heat.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>If a cold Air immediately ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Summer-heat, there will be occaſion'd, for the moſt part, that day, the retention of about a pound of the inſenſible excrements.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>If the Summer prove like the Spring, ſo as that mens bodies may be reduc'd to the weight anſwerable to the Summer, it
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102101:39"/>muſt be the effect of Sweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>At the beginning of Summer, if intenſe heat come of a ſudden, wearineſs and faintneſs enſue, which do not continue long though the ſultrineſs be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd for ſome daies after, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the weight of the perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable body is abated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>The ſame vigour is not ſo much concern'd in ſtrugling with a leſſer, as it is with a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er weight of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>Perſpiration procur'd by the force of warm air or water, is hurtful, unleſs the malignancy of it be not ballanc'd by ſome greater benefit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>Robuſt bodies perſpire more
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102101:39"/>in the Summer time, by day, in the Winter, by night.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>That impediment of reſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which in the Summer-time is apt to be introductory to a malignant Feaver, does hardly in the winter-time cauſe the leaſt alternation: for, in the ſummer, mens bodies are fill'd with a perſpirable matter of a ſharper nature, than they are in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>To ſleep in the Summer-time with the body uncover'd, or abroad in the open Air, does for the moſt part diſpoſe it to putrefaction, by hindring the perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVII.</head>
                  <p>The difficulty of reſpiration does not heat the entrails, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the perſpirable matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102101:40"/>ſharp by reaſon of its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, or upon the account of external heat, or violent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>In the Summer-time when cold does of a ſudden ſucceed heat, the inconvenience of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Venery is hardly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd: but if the Air reaſſume its former warmth, men are very ſenſible of the injury they have receiv'd by the precedent miſcarriage.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIX.</head>
                  <p>The injury men receive by the not-immoderate exerciſe of Venery is commonly ballanc'd by an equal benefit, if the heat be concentrated by the cool Air.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XL.</head>
                  <p>In the Summer-nights mens bodies are moſt diſpos'd to Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102101:40"/>by reaſon of the viciſſitude of the Air; for at the beginning of the night, the Air is enflam'd, but about midnight it is more temperate, and in the morning cool; whence it comes to paſs, that the uſual perſpirable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not evacuated in ſuch as ſleep with the Bed-cloaths off, and their bodies are more pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous; which happens not in winter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLI.</head>
                  <p>From the Autumnal Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nox to the Winter Solſtice, we perſpire every day much about a pound: from thence to the Spring-Equinox we begin to perſpire more freely.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLII.</head>
                  <p>Autumn is an unhealthy ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as well by reaſon that the perſpiration is obſtructed by the cold then coming in, as for that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102101:41"/>what is not perſpir'd becomes ſharp, and corroding.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIII.</head>
                  <p>Autumnal indiſpoſitions are avoided, if the body be not of greater weight in Autumn than it had been in Summer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIV.</head>
                  <p>That weight which is aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by degrees, is to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated by degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLV.</head>
                  <p>The more than uſual weight of the body is not to be taken off in the Spring, but in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn; for the cold air then coming in is a greater enemy to the weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVI.</head>
                  <p>Thou wilt not be troubled with any diſeaſe in Autumn, if the cold weather then coming in find thee well furniſh'd with cloaths, if thou uſe diureticks,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:102101:41"/>and wilt be kept in the ſame weight as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVII.</head>
                  <p>He who is well cloath'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires the better for it, and is rendered of leſs weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVIII.</head>
                  <p>They who in the Winter-time are commonly troubled with diſeaſes proceeding from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of humours, are to be purg'd in Autumn, and not in the Spring, and ought to be reduc'd to the weight they were of at the beginning of Summer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIX.</head>
                  <p>But if the diſeaſes proceed from ſome malignant quality, the bodies are to be purg'd in the Spring, and not in Autumn; for the malignancy of the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is more augmented in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, than in Winter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:102101:42"/>
                  <head>L.</head>
                  <p>They who at the beginning of the Spring deveſt themſelves too ſoon, and in Autumn are backward in putting on their winter-garments, are, in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, apt to fall into Feavers, and in Winter, to be troubled with diſtillations.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LI.</head>
                  <p>The retention of the perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable matter, as it has a ſharp quality, cauſes Feavers, and Eryſipelas's; as to its redundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, it cauſes Apoſtems, Diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or an evil habit of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LII.</head>
                  <p>External cold, by concentra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the heat, makes nature ſo much the ſtronger, by how much it is the more able to bear about two pounds of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable matter unevacuated
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102101:42"/>over and above its ordinary weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIII.</head>
                  <p>At the beginning of winter, mens bodies are eaſily reduc'd to their uſual weight; but in the beginning of Summer, it is with much ado that they are reduc'd to the Summer-weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIV.</head>
                  <p>There would be an uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted healthfulneſs even to the extremity of age, if mens bodies were kept in an equal weight during the four ſeaſons of the year.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LV.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe bodies whoſe weights are much augmented and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the ſpace of a year, are in great danger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVI.</head>
                  <p>The greater variety there is of the weight of any body in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102101:43"/>the ſpace of a year; and the greater the augmentation or diminution of the blood is, ſo much the worſe is the condition of that body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVII.</head>
                  <p>The augmentation of the weight happens at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Autumn, the diminution at the beginning of Summer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVIII.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe bodies, whoſe weight is augmented, are in a more dangerous condition, than thoſe whoſe weight is diminiſh'd.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:102101:43"/>
               <head>APHORISMS <hi>Added by the Author.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="59" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIX.</head>
                  <p>THoſe parts of the body which are cover'd do health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully perſpite; but if they be found uncover'd after ſleep, their pores are condenſated by even the warmeſt air.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LX.</head>
                  <p>That air, which is over cool, moiſt, or windy, obſtructs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration: whence it happens, that ſuch as keep within doors, as for example Women, are not troubled with Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hs, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarrhes, or inflammations of the lungs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:102101:44"/>
                  <head>LXI.</head>
                  <p>The City air is worſe than that of the Country; becauſe it is more thick, and, not rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd by the wind, takes away the appetite.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:102101:44"/>
            <head>OF MEAT <hi>and</hi> DRINK.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT.</hi> III.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>Aphoriſm I.</head>
                  <p>IF the Stomach fill'd with meat does, while the body ſleeps, compleat the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, the perſpiration of that night does commonly amount to forty ounces; if it does not compleat it, it comes to but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eighteen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>If the Stomach be quite empty and faſting, though the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102101:45"/>party ſleep, he does not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire above eighteen ounces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>A full body, that does not concoct, perſpires much about the ſame rate as one in a manner faſting, that has not any thing to concoct.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Meats that are very nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mutton only excepted, from ſupper over night to din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the next day, do not uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally perſpire above eighteen ounces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Many who feed plentifully on meats of little nouriſhment, may, in the ſpace of one night, perſpire above forty ounces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe aliments which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue bodies in their uſual weight are either thoſe of very
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102101:45"/>much nouriſhment, or ſuch as cauſe obſtinate crudities.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe which continue them in their uſual lightneſs are ſuch as they are accuſtomed to, and eaſily evaporated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Mutton is eaſily concocted, and vaporous; for in a night's ſpace it perſpires one third part of a pound more than other meats, and ſuch as a man is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>The meats which are made of leavened paſte do not make bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies more ponderous, for they perſpire more eaſily, than tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neps.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>A healthy perſon does inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly exhale as much in the ſpace of one day, as he does by
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:102101:46"/>ſtool in a fortnight; nay though he once every day evacuate the concocted and conſiſtent faeces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>The full Stomach, and the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty, diminiſh the perſpiration; the full ſtomach diverts it, by the corruption of meats; the empty attracts it, that it may be fill'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>When the full Stomach does not compleat the concoction, is diſcover'd by the weight; for then the body perſpires leſs; but the empty ſtomach is fill'd with wind.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>Windineſs is nothing elſe but an imperfect kind of perſpirable matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>The robuſt perſon conſumes his plentiful feeding by inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſpiration; one leſs robuſt,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102101:46"/>by urine; a weak perſon, for the moſt part, by the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the chyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>When a man forbears ſupping, the ſtomach being empty, and no paroxyſm preſſing upon a man, there is a retention of the perſpirable matter, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing retain'd becomes ſharp, and thereupon the body is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for hot diſtempers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>That abſtinence from meat which reduces mens bodies to a leſſer weight, but withal ſuch as is unuſual to them, is hurtful.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>Why are there ſome that die of Hunger, if there be never any defect of blood in the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing creature? Becauſe the blood, making to the empty part of the belly, forſakes the heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:102101:47"/>
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>Undigeſted meat, not only as to its quantity, but alſo as to its quality, makes the body more ponderous, inaſmuch as it hinders Perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>When any one ſeems to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf lighter than he is, and yet is not ſo, 'tis a very good ſign; for this proceeds from the Juices of the three Concoctions exactly digeſted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>When there is a lightneſs and agility of the body felt for a whole day together, it argues there preceeded a concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the chyle and blood, and that the Dregs, as it were, of the third concoction are almoſt evacuated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>Undigeſted meat, the more
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102101:47"/>full of nouriſhment it is, is ſo much the worſe, either becauſe it cauſes a greater weight or a worſe corruption.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>The body is rendred moſt light by the corruption of meat; for all the liquid excrements are of great weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>The uſe of Swines-fleſh, and Muſhrooms is hurtful, as well becauſe theſe do not perſpire, as becauſe they ſuffer not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meats eaten with them to perſpire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>Upon the eating of Swines-fleſh and Muſhrooms the body commonly perſpires leſs than it is wont by a third part of a pound.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>Melons perſpire ſo little, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102101:48"/>they abate about a fourth part of the uſual perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>That retention of the perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration cauſed by Melons is eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated by Urine, or Sweating.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>Grapes and green Figs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire but little, and ſomewhat hinder the perſpiration of other meats; haply becauſe they are ſenſibly evacuated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>That kind of food does per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire beſt of all, and convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nouriſhes, whoſe weight is not felt in the belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>Plentiful feeding is more hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in a ſedentary and idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than in one that is employ'd; for the entrails are made heavy by reſt, but are eas'd of their weight by exerciſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:102101:48"/>
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>The body perſpires beſt after that meat, whoſe faeces are emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a certain conſiſtency.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>Chickens-fleſh ſhall be of leſs nouriſhment than a Lettice, if a man eat ſo plentifully thereof, as that it cannot be evacuated otherwiſe than by the way of liquid faeces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>By ponderation you will find out when faſting conduces to your Health, and when it does not: it will be healthful, if there be any thing of the precedent day's refection left to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd, if there be not, it will be unhealthful.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>When the body is reduc'd by diet to a weight below the leſſer ſtandard of its healthy weight,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102101:49"/>what it loſes of its ſtrength is irrecoverable. But that there is a leſſer and greater weight in reference to Health, you will find by the LXIV. Aphoriſm of the firſt Section, and by the XL. of this third.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>If thou canſt but find out eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day what quantity of meat is convenient for thee, thou wilt know how to preſerve thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and life a long time, and that thou wilt diſcover by the ſame Aphoriſm.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>The ſtrength of nature is not a little impair'd, when a man's ſupper amounts ſometimes to four pound, ſometimes to ſix.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>That is the moſt healthful proportion of meat, when after eating, the body performs what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102101:49"/>it has to do with the ſame agility, as if it were faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVII.</head>
                  <p>The body alſo is much more burthen'd by eight pounds of meat eaten in a day at one meal, than by ten pounds taken in the ſame ſpace of time at three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral meals.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>That quantity of meat is the moſt wholſom for every man, which may without any trouble be overcome by the concoctive faculty; and that is done, if ſo much be conſum'd as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into the body; for theſe things will be diſcover'd by ponderation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIX.</head>
                  <p>That quantity of meat is to be receiv'd into the body, which nature is able to concoct, digeſt, and perſpire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:102101:50"/>
                  <head>XL.</head>
                  <p>If nature could digeſt a hundred pound weight of meat, and there be given but ninety nine pounds, the animal would upon that account be deſtroy'd in proceſs of time.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLI.</head>
                  <p>Then will meats of good nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment and juice promiſe thee a long continuance of health, when the quantity of perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in the mean, between exceſs and defect: The exceſs, after a plentiful ſupper of meats of eaſy perſpiration commonly amounts, in the ſpace of one night, to forty ounces or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, the defect but to four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen. That proportion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of meat, which will bring thee to two and twenty ounces, which is the mean between the other two, will promiſe thee
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102101:50"/>infallible health and long life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLII.</head>
                  <p>The opinion of <hi>Celſus</hi> is not ſafe for all perſons, to wit, that in the uſe of the ſix not natural things, men ought ſometimes to be ſparing, and ſometimes to exceed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIII.</head>
                  <p>Bodies are with leſs trouble reduc'd to their uſual weight, if men take four pounds of meat at dinner, and four at ſupper, obſerving a convenient interval, than if they take ſix at dinner and two at ſupper.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIV.</head>
                  <p>That perſon deſtroyes himſelf by degrees, who eats once a day beſides his ordinary meals, whether he eat little or much.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLV.</head>
                  <p>The body is made more pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerous by four ounces of meat
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102101:51"/>that is of much nutriment, ſuch as Pork, Eeles, and all fat things, than by ſix ounces of meat that is of little nouriſhment, ſuch as are ſmall Fiſhes, Chickens, ſmall Birds; and the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVI.</head>
                  <p>If there be any difficulty in the concoction of meat which is of littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nouriſhment, it will happen only in the firſt concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but if there be a difficulty in the concoction of meat of much nutriment, it will happen in all the concoctions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVII.</head>
                  <p>Meat of little nutriment moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens and looſens the belly, is ſoon digeſted, and readily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes the perſpiration of men whether ſleeping or waking.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVIII.</head>
                  <p>Meat of much nutriment binds the belly, if it be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:102101:51"/>corrupted, is of difficult con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, and perſpires little.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIX.</head>
                  <p>Where there is a difficulty of concoction, there is but a ſlow perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <head>L.</head>
                  <p>Not that meat which is fluid, but that which is of better juice ought to be eaten firſt; for the Pylorus, or Stomach-gut, is not at the bottom, in men, as it is in Dogs</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LI.</head>
                  <p>Three inconveniences are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to mens feeding on va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of meats; there is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of eating, the concoction is leſs, and the perſpiration leſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LII.</head>
                  <p>The time of leaſt perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, when the ſtomach is full, eſpecially with variety ſo meats.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:102101:52"/>
                  <head>LIII.</head>
                  <p>They who vomit up their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per do immediately remove the pain of their ſtomach, but the next morning, they feel their bodies more ponderous: for vomiting diverts perſpiration, by attracting the perſpirable matter to the inward parts; which matter, upon the ſcore of its being ſharp cauſes laſſitude and heat, upon that of its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundancy, it cauſes heavineſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIV.</head>
                  <p>That perſon, who eats more than is requiſite, is nouriſh'd leſs than is requiſite.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LV.</head>
                  <p>They who in their youth are immoderate in their diet, make the Stomach larger than it ſhould be, whence it comes to paſs, that it proves a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to reduce them afterwards to a moderate diet.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:102101:52"/>
                  <head>LVI.</head>
                  <p>If any one be deſirous to be reduc'd to a moderate diet, let him uſe food of little nutriment, and ſo the Stomach ſoon diſbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening it ſelf of it, will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, and reduc'd to a leſs capacity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVII.</head>
                  <p>You will find what quantity of meat you ſhould eat, if for ſeveral daies together you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that the body after ſleep is without any trouble, reduc'd to the ſame weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVIII.</head>
                  <p>If after a plentiful ſupper the body be of leſs weight the next day, it happens either by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the corruption of the meat, or becauſe nature is ſtir'd up to expel that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial, which is extreamly hurtfull: for the body is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:102101:53"/>for diſeaſes when thoſe things which are beneficial are evacuated, and crudities kept within the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIX.</head>
                  <p>If a man's ſupper amount to eight pounds, and what he has eaten be corrupted in the ſtomach, the next day the body will be of leſs weight, than if the ſupper had been of three pounds, and the meat had not been corrupted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LX.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe meats that are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to perſpiration are not corrupted, nay after watching whole nights, they keep a man from wearineſs and heavineſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXI.</head>
                  <p>Meats not apt to perſpire are wont to cauſe obſtructions, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, laſſitude, penſiveneſs, and ponderoſity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:102101:53"/>
                  <head>LXII.</head>
                  <p>Then is a living creature in the worſt condition, when after the concoction is compleated, the body ſeems to be more bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome than ordinary, while yet it is of leſs weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXIII.</head>
                  <p>If any one has been exceſſive in eating or drinking, and there enſue thereupon ſuch ſenſible evacuations as are greater than uſual, the body is, next day, lighter than uſual.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXIV.</head>
                  <p>Liquid meats, ſuppoſing an equality as to quantity, are more ponderous than the ſolid: the liquids go to the bottom, the ſolid keep on the top: a cup of wine, or meſs of Broath is of more weight, than a whole loaf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:102101:54"/>
                  <head>LXV.</head>
                  <p>If exceſs in drinking make the Eies as't were full of tears, it is a ſign the body has not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pir'd as much as it ſhould have done.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXVI.</head>
                  <p>If after much drinking, you ſweat, or urine much, it is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of either great ſtrength or great weakneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXVII.</head>
                  <p>The drinking of cold water obſtructs inſenſible perſpiration, but augments the ſenſible.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXVIII.</head>
                  <p>In theſe our daies, Drinking, even in temperate perſons, is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionate: for men eat com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly after the rate of twelve Ounces, but drink, after that of forty, and above.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXIX.</head>
                  <p>In a man of moderate diet,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:102101:54"/>the nocturnal perſpiration ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times amounts to three pound; in a perſon who feeds plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the ſtomach being empty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſtrong, it may amount to five pounds.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXX.</head>
                  <p>If a body be in its ſtandard of greater weight, faſting is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to it, if in its mean, it is hurtful, if in its leſſer weight, it is much more hurtful.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXI.</head>
                  <p>If after long faſting the body be plentifully fed, the perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amounts to a pound more than it uſually does.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXII.</head>
                  <p>To eat immediately after im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate exerciſe of body or mind, is hurtful; for the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried body perſpires with ſome difficulty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="73" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:102101:55"/>
                  <head>LXXIII.</head>
                  <p>When ſober perſons and ſuch as are moderate in their diet die betimes, their friends wonder at the ſtrangeneſs of it, becauſe they know nothing of inſenſible perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="74" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXIV.</head>
                  <p>Exceſs of meat and drink does not only keep the acrimony of the perſpirable matter which is retain'd lurking in the body, but alſo the deprav'd affections of the parts, eſpecially of thoſe that are not the principal, and that for a long time; which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, when the bodies are purg'd, or brought low by much faſting, break forth of a ſudden, and turn into violent diſtempers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="75" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXV.</head>
                  <p>That Phyſician who is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate the diet of Princes, if he
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:102101:55"/>be ignorant, how much, and when they daily perſpire, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes, and does not cure them, and if he do them any good, it is by chance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="76" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXVI.</head>
                  <p>For about the ſpace of four hours after meat, moſt people do hardly perſpire a pound, thence to the ninth hour, two pound, from the ninth to the ſixteenth, hardly a pound.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="77" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXVII.</head>
                  <p>Then is it the proper time to take refection, when the body ſhall be reduc'd to that weight, yet healthful, which it was of a little before the party had eaten the day before. And this only
<hi>Apollo</hi> himſelf ſhall find out without the Ballance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="78" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>But if the unuſual weight of the over-night's drinking be not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:102101:56"/>taken off, either by the ſtrength of the concoctive faculty, or by corruption the next day, take the advice of theſe two verſes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Si nocturna tibi noceat potatio vini,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hoc tu manè bibas iterum, &amp; fuerit medicina.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If overnight thou tak'ſt a doſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And find'ſt thy ſelf amiſs,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou muſt next morn another take:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>No remedy like this.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="79" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXIX.</head>
                  <p>If the healthful weight of the body, after ſupper, amount to two hundred pound weight, the body being rendred leſs healthful by immoderate vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall weigh about a hundred
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:102101:56"/>ninety eight pounds, becauſe that remiſſion of vigour is the hindrance, why two pounds of the aliments cannot, at leaſt without ſome trouble or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, be converted into the healthful weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="80" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXX.</head>
                  <p>Meat of eaſy perſpiration does more eaſily, and with much leſs trouble recruit the waſted ſtrength of thoſe who uſe vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, than does that of difficult perſpiration, or of much nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="81" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXI.</head>
                  <p>New Wine, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what muddy, if it be concocted in the Stomach, does not only perſpire it ſelf, but very much promotes the perſpiration of other meats. This quality alſo have thoſe hot things that are flatulent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="82" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:102101:57"/>
                  <head>LXXXII.</head>
                  <p>Onions, Garlick, Mutton, Pheaſants, but above all the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaick juice promote the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of meats not eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>APHORISMS <hi>Added by the Author.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="83" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXIII.</head>
                  <p>A Very ſmall quantity of food is not imbrac'd by the Stomach. Thence comes it, that it is not concocted, it does not nouriſh, it does not perſpire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="84" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXIV.</head>
                  <p>Inſenſible perſpiration is an excrement of the third con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:102101:57"/>if therefore the firſt concoction be not performed, neither will the third.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="85" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXV.</head>
                  <p>If that quantity of food which amounts to about four pound be hurtful, taken all at once in a day, the ſame quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity divided into two or three meals may be healthful: the repletion of the belly diverts inſenſible evacuation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="86" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXVI.</head>
                  <p>The inconveniencies attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing extraordinary faſting are theſe, the Head is fill'd with humours, the Temples beat, the Hypochondries are dilated, and a wearineſs of the arms &amp; thighs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="87" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXVII.</head>
                  <p>That emptineſs of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach which is occaſion'd by the ſcantineſs of meat, is greater than that which is occaſion'd by
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:102101:58"/>Phyſick; which Latter does indeed excite ſenſible evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but diverts the inſenſible.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="88" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>In Phlegmatick conſtitutions, if the Stomach be empty in the morning, by reaſon of their not having ſupp'd the night before, dry food is very beneficial, ſuch as bisket.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="89" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXXXIX.</head>
                  <p>No man will fall into any diſeaſe, if he carefully provide that he be not troubled with crudities.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="90" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XC.</head>
                  <p>It is ſafer for aged perſons to take their refection thrice in a day, as <hi>Antiochus</hi> did, than twice, or to eat much at once; for it much obſtructs perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="91" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCI.</head>
                  <p>Why did not <hi>Antiochus</hi> eat
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:102101:58"/>Fiſh at ſupper? Becauſe they hinder perſpiration: After ſleep perſpiration is very good, which not performed, there is a remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſtrength and vigour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="92" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCII.</head>
                  <p>The coldneſs and clammineſs of the juice of cucumbers is kept in the veins, nay other unwholſome juices though of eaſy concoction, by obſtructing the perſpiration, cauſe malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Feavers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="93" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCIII.</head>
                  <p>Why does the corruption of meat cauſe wearineſs? Becauſe it diverts perſpiration. But how? Becauſe it cauſes the coeliack diſeaſe. But why does the coeliack diſeaſe cauſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs? Becauſe there comes out along with the excrements ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the former well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="94" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:102101:59"/>
                  <head>XCIV.</head>
                  <p>If any one goes with a tyr'd body to ſupper, or to waſh himſelf, there enſues, immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after ſleep, a certain chilneſs over the body, and wearineſs; yet about twelve hours after ſupper, all is well again; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then the concoction and perſpiration is good.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="95" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCV.</head>
                  <p>Meat after violent exerciſe is hurtful, as well by reaſon it is not embrac'd, as that it diverts Perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="96" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCVI.</head>
                  <p>He who goes to ſupper with a diſturbed mind, digeſts much leſs than another, who is undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd and cheerful.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="97" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCVII.</head>
                  <p>Drinking between dinner and ſupper is hurtful: but if we drink ſo much the leſs at
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:102101:59"/>ſupper, the hurtfulneſs is taken off.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="98" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCVIII.</head>
                  <p>Vomiting after ſupper weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens a man, not only upon this ſcore, that it voids the aliment, but alſo becauſe it diverts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="99" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XCIX.</head>
                  <p>If a man exceed in meat and drink once or twice in a month, though he does not ſenſibly eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate the next day, yet he weighs leſs than uſual.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="100" type="aphorism">
                  <head>C.</head>
                  <p>He who confines himſelf to a regular diet, wants the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences of thoſe perſons, who exceed once or twice a month: for the expulſive faculty being ſtirr'd up by redundancy excites ſo great a perſpiration, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Staticks no body would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="101" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:102101:60"/>
                  <head>CI.</head>
                  <p>In a cold body, hony is good, becauſe it nouriſhes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires; in a hot, it is hurtful, becauſe it turns into choler.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="102" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CII.</head>
                  <p>Nothing more obſtructs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, than for a man to drink while the chyle is prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="103" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CIII.</head>
                  <p>The Liver does not attract the chyle, by reaſon of its cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, much leſs does it expel the perſpirable matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="104" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CIV.</head>
                  <p>In a healthy man, if the belly be looſe, it either happens through ſome defect in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, or the diſtribution of the chyle, by reaſon of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="105" type="aphorism">
                  <head>CV.</head>
                  <p>There are two things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:102101:60"/>prejudicial to good health, <hi>viz.</hi> to give up the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wholly to a ſlothful repoſe, and to eat, before the concoction of what had been eaten before.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:102101:61"/>
            <head>OF SLEEP AND VIGILANCE.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT.</hi> IV.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>Aphoriſm I.</head>
                  <p>UNdiſturbed ſleep is ſo great a promoter of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, that, in the ſpace of ſeven hours, fifty ounces of the concocted perſpirable matter do commonly exhale out of ſtrong bodies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:102101:61"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>A man ſleeping the ſpace of ſeven hours is wont, inſenſibly, healthfully, and without any vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, to perſpire twice as much as one awake.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>That perſpiration of a ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſon, which is attended with much ſweating, is not more plentiful, than any kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible Perſpiration, without ſweating.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>After a good night's reſt, the body is felt of leſs weight, as well by reaſon of the augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſtrength, as by that of the exhalation of at the leaſt about three pounds of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Diſturbed ſleep does com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly obſtruct one third part
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:102101:62"/>of a pound of the uſual Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>In undiſturbed reſt, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration is ſometimes greater, allowing the ſame proportion of time, than in violent exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>In the morning-ſleep, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the compleating of the firſt concoction, a pound of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable Excrements do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly exhale in the ſpace of one hour, but if it be not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, there is not a fourth part exhal'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe things which hinder ſleeping do alſo obſtruct the Perſpiration of the concocted perſpirable matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>Short ſleeping proceeds from
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:102101:62"/>the acrimony of the perſpirable matter, which is not evacuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but the retention of the perſpirable matter is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occaſion'd, by Nature's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more than uſually employ'd about ſome other internal functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>The acrimony of the perſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able matter which is retain'd, very often aſcends up to the head, diſturbs ſleep, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the perſpiration of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>If any one, after ſleep, feels a kind of pain in his armes, or imagines them more than uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wearied, it is an argument that the body is of greater weight, than nature can long endure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>They who ſleep with their
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:102101:63"/>feet and legs uncover'd, are depriv'd of as much perſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as may amount to a pound in the ſpace of one night.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>A continual agitation of the body in bed is more diſturbant than ſwift running; for in the motion of a perſon running, the muſcles only of the inferiour parts are mov'd, in that of a perſon lying along, the muſcles of the whole body in a manner are in motion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>Perſpiration is more obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in perſons ſleeping, by a cool ſoutherly gale of wind, than it is in perſons awake by a great cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>If the night's reſt be leſs than uſual, there is a diminution in the exhalation of the conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:102101:63"/>perſpirable matter, but the perſpiration of crudities is augmented.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>After meats of eaſy perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration mens bodies are rendred rather weak than weighty; but after thoſe of difficult per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, they become both weak and weighty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>The perſpiration occaſion'd by ſleep differs in ſpecies from that which comes by vigilance; the former implies the evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of concocted perſpirables without acrimony, and with a recruiting of the ſtrength; the latter, that of crudities, and is ſharp, violent, and with ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>A perſon ſleeping perſpires twice as much as one waking.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:102101:64"/>Thence came that remarkable ſaying, Two hours of reſt in a perſon awake are but equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to one of ſleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>I have found by experience, that in the ſpace of ſeven hours, the inſenſible perſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in a perſon ſleeping, as to many, amounted to about forty ounces; in one awake, but to twenty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>He who goes to bed with an empty Stomach perſpires that night about a third part leſs than he is wont to do.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>Perſons of a cholerick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution who go to bed with a ſtomach quite empty, have theſe inconveniencies; the belly and head are fill'd with crudities, their temples beat their fleſh
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:102101:64"/>waſtes away, they are troubled with vehement ſtretchings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the armes and hands, ſometimes a heart-burning, or corroſion of the mouth of the Stomach, vertigo's and epile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſies; as it happen'd to <hi>Diodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>After a perſpiration greater than we are wont to have, a more plentiful ſupper promiſes a longer and founder ſleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>A leſs than the uſual perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the foreteller of diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſleep, and a troubleſom night.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>If after a ſhort and unquiet ſleep, the fleſh be found cold, and that thereupon a feveriſh fit ſucceeds, in weak perſons it commonly preſignifies death,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:102101:65"/>in ſtrong, a long continuance of ſickneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>By change of lodging ſleep is diſturbed, and the perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is leſs. For unwonted things, though better, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to body and mind.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>Men dream more in a bed they are not accuſtom'd to, than in that they conſtantly ly in.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>They who ſleep and do not dream perſpire well, and ſo on the contrary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>Sleep about four hours after meat is beſt; for then nature is leaſt employ'd about the firſt concoction, it better recruits what was loſt, and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:102101:65"/>
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>If about five hours after ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per you weigh a perſon juſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wak'd out of his ſleep, you will find that he hardly perſpir'd a pound; if it be done eight hours after ſleep, you will find that he has perſpir'd three pound.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>If a mans ſleep be ſhorter than it is wont to be, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the perſpiration ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, which if it be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair'd in the ſubſequent daies by a more plentiful perſpiration, there is ſome danger of a Feaver.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>If there be a retention of any part of the uſual perſpiration, the next day, or after dinner, we are overcome with ſleep, and in an hours ſpace perſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a pound: or the night fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:102101:66"/>lowing, our ſleep is ſo much the longer, the more expedient it was that we ſhould perſpire more than uſually; otherwiſe we fall into a ſenſible criſis, or into a diſeaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>Oſcitation, and the ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the joints after ſleep de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note that the body has perſpir'd very well, as it is related of Cocks, ſmiting themſelves with their wings before they crow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>The oſcitations and extenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the joints and limbs, which happen immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſleep, are rais'd out of the plenty of perſpirables excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently well prepar'd for eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>Mens bodies perſpire more in half an hours ſpace, by yawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:102101:66"/>gaping, and ſtretching out of the body, than in three hours of any other time.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>They who adminiſter ſyrups, or other medicines to ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons during the time of their beſt perſpiration, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly for the ſpace of two hours after ſleep, injure them; but in the ſubſequent hours they do them good.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>In Paroxyſmes, or any great fits of ſickneſs, gaping and ſtretching of the body ſignify the concentration of the heat, but the evacuation of a great quantity of acrimonious perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter that had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVII.</head>
                  <p>In an hours ſleep at noon, after meat, mens bodies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:102101:67"/>evacuate ſometimes a pound, ſometimes half a pound of excrements inſenſibly perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; a pound, if there be ought retain'd of the precedent day's perſpiration; half a pound, if nothing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>If ought of the precedent day's Perſpiration be retain'd, and that it be not evacuated by ſleeping at noon, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after Sleep, there is felt a great heavineſs of the head, and a very afflictive pain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIX.</head>
                  <p>If within four hours after ſleep the meat a man has eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en be corrupted, immediately theſe two inconveniences mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually conſequent one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will follow, to wit, an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Perſpiration, and Watching.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:102101:67"/>
                  <head>XL.</head>
                  <p>There is no cauſe does more frequently interrupt ſleep, than the corruption of a man's meat. This is caus'd by the Sympathy there is between the Stomach, and the Brain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLI.</head>
                  <p>Sleep is better in Winter, than in Summer, not becauſe men's bellies are hotter, or their ſleep longer, but becauſe before day-light their bodieis are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually hotter, and as ſuch are apt to perſpire very much, whereas in Summer they are more cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLII.</head>
                  <p>Purity of diſcourſe, and agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of body after ſleep are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications, that the body has perſpir'd that night commonly at leaſt three pound.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:102101:68"/>
                  <head>XLIII.</head>
                  <p>Lightneſs of the head after ſleep at noon, denotes that there had not been any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd of the precedent day's Perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIV.</head>
                  <p>Sleep moiſtens all the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and internal parts, becauſe it attenuates the perſpirable matter, and being ſo attenuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it diſperſes it into all the members.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLV.</head>
                  <p>Vigilance ſtirs from the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre to the circumference that blood which is leſs prepar'd for Perſpiration than it is in ſuch as are aſleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVI.</head>
                  <p>By Sleep the humours are concentrated, the influent heat is united to the innate, thirſt is taken away, unleſs Choler be
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:102101:68"/>predominant, there is a conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made of the blood into the ſecond moiſtures, and the bodies become lighter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVII.</head>
                  <p>By Sleep the animal ſpirits languiſh; by Vigilance, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and natural ſpirits lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVIII.</head>
                  <p>By Vigilance the animal ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are corroborated, but the vital and natural languiſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIX.</head>
                  <p>By Sleep the internal parts are more heated, and are alſo made more light. By Vigilance the external parts are made more hot, and alſo more light.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                  <head>L.</head>
                  <p>By too much ſleep the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and external parts grow cold, the humours are forcibly crowded in, and made imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:102101:69"/>and the bodies are ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred more ponderous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LI.</head>
                  <p>Cholerick bodies are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly prejudiced by exceſſive ſleeping, not becauſe the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the third concoction are made imperſpirable, but becauſe they become extream ſharp, and are afterwards noxious to the head and other entrails.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LII.</head>
                  <p>In perſons ſleeping with the bed cloaths caſt off, perſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is more obſtructed than it is in perſons awake who have no cloaths on; as well by reaſon of the quiet poſture of ſuch as are aſleep, as alſo for that the heat of the external parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats inward.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIII.</head>
                  <p>A more than uſual watching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enders men's bodies, during
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:102101:69"/>the firſt ſubſequent days after it, more ponderous, and more weak. They are more ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, becauſe after the evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the perſpirable excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there is left behind a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain juice, which, of it ſelf, is crude, and, by accident, ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; they are weaker, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe where there is any cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, there is no converſion made, and conſequently the ſtrength is impair'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIV.</head>
                  <p>If after immoderate watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man ſleep ſeven hours, the Perſpiration will be more than uſual, by about a pound.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LV.</head>
                  <p>Continued watching renders mens bodies more ponderous, not by reaſon of the greater Perſpiration, or ſenſible evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, but becauſe the recruit
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:102101:70"/>of fat and fleſh is not anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to what had been waſted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVI.</head>
                  <p>In the morning the body both is, and is felt leſs ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; it is ſo, becauſe by the precedent ſleep three pound of perſpirable excrements were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuated; it is ſo felt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe it is lighter, but alſo in regard that by the concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the meats that were eaſily perſpirable, there is an augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſtrength.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVII.</head>
                  <p>A man's body may become more ponderous by unuſual watching, if the meat, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is fed, be unfit for perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LVIII.</head>
                  <p>There is ſo plentiful an exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the body in perſons ſteeping, that not only the ſick
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:102101:70"/>lying with the ſound, but alſo the ſound among themſelves do mutually communicate their good or evil diſpoſitions.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>APHORISMS <hi>Added by the Author.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="59" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LIX.</head>
                  <p>AFter meat ſleep; after ſleep concoction; after concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tranſpiration is beſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LX.</head>
                  <p>Diacydonium, or Marmalet, not taken immediately after ſupper but after the firſt ſleep, excites ſleep, provided there be nothing drunk after it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXI.</head>
                  <p>Diacydonium, or Marmalet, taken with a little Cinnamon
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:102101:71"/>ſtrengtheneth the ſtomach; and that being ſtrengthened, ſleep alwaies follows.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXII.</head>
                  <p>A ſmall quantity of Generous Wine and Garlick cauſe ſleep and perſpiration, but if a man take more than is requiſite, they obſtruct both; however they convert the perſpirable matter into ſweating.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXIII.</head>
                  <p>That man will doubtleſs come to a great age, who does daily concoct and digeſt well; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction is caus'd by ſleep and reſt; digeſtion by vigilance and exerciſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXIV.</head>
                  <p>If the wearineſs enſuing after ſleep be taken off by uſual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, the defect was in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, and not in the concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:102101:71"/>
                  <head>LXV.</head>
                  <p>When we riſe from ſleep with our uſual weight, but with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er unweildineſs, if it be not taken off by our accuſtomed exerciſe, it ſigniſies an accumulation of crudities, corruption of meat, or immoderate coition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXVI.</head>
                  <p>Unuſual ſleeping at noon is hurtful to all the entrails, and checks perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXVII.</head>
                  <p>Wearineſs or unweildineſs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſleep is taken off by thoſe things which facilitate perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: Theſe are abſtinence, exerciſe, vigilance, and anger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXVIII.</head>
                  <p>If the body lie looſe and flat, ſleep is hurtful; if it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, it is good: the entrails lying cloſe and compacted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther havean eaſy concoction, but
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:102101:72"/>when they are looſe by one's ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at length, they have a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult concoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXIX.</head>
                  <p>If in ſound perſons, a cold ſweat enſue after ſleep, it argues they perſpire leſs than they ſhould do, and in proceſs of time, if the ſame thing happens, they are troubled with the Gout.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="aphorism">
                  <head>LXX.</head>
                  <p>By immoderate ſleep, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive drinking of Wine the ſtrength is ſuffocated; by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive vigilance and exerciſe, it is diſſolved: all theſe dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhconcoction, and that dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, there is a ſtoppage of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:102101:72"/>
            <head>OF EXERCISE AND REST.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT.</hi> V.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>Aphoriſm I.</head>
                  <p>THE occult perſpiration of a mans body is leſs, in violent motion, than it is in the morning, nine or ten hours from the time he had ſupp'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>That which is evacuated in
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:102101:73"/>violent motion by the pores is ſweat, and an occult perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter: but, as it is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, it is rais'd for the moſt part out of unconcocted juices: for it ſeldom happens that there ſhould be ſo great a collection of concocted perſpirable matter in the body, as is evacuated by violence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Sweating alwaies proceeds from a violent cauſe, and as ſuch (as ſtatical experiments make it appear) it obſtructs the occult evacuation of concocted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>The body perſpires much more lying quietly in bed, than turning from one ſide to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by frequent agitation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Chearful and angry perſons
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:102101:73"/>are leſs wearied by long travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, than the fearful and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive: for the former perſpire more healthfully, but the other, leſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe bodies which are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to refection after immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate exerciſe, receive much prejudice; becauſe, as they are wearied and burthen'd with meat, they perſpire leſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>Exerciſe from the ſeventh hour to the twelfth after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, does inſenſibly diſſolve more in the ſpace of one hour, than it does in three hours at any other time.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Inſenſible evacuation after violent exerciſe obſtructs the ſucceſſive recruiting of that which is waſted: nay if the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:102101:74"/>ſame violence ſhould continue, the body will be rendred ſo light, that in many there would be ſome danger of a future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>By exerciſe mens bodies are made lighter: for all the parts, eſpecially the muſcles and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments are cleans'd from excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by motion, the perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter is prepar'd for exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and the ſpirits are made more tenuious, or ſubtil.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>Motion prepares bodies for the evacuation of ſenſible and inſenſible excrements; reſt does it rather for that of the inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible only.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>If the body lye quietly in the bed after ſupper for the ſpace of ten hours, it ſhall perſpire
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:102101:74"/>excellently well: if it reſt there yet ſomewhat longer, there follows immediately a diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of both ſenſible and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible evacuation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>Long reſt renders indiſpos'd bodies more weighty, as well in regard the perſpirable excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are prepar'd for evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by motion, as alſo for that the meat and drink, if ſuch as the patient is not accuſtom'd to, or more in quantity than is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, are not digeſted; and thence proceed all inconveniences, and many times death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>If a perſon who has kept his bed long be troubled with pain in the feet, the remedy is walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; if one that is upon a jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney be ſo troubled, the remedy is reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:102101:75"/>
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>There are two kinds of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, one of the body, the other of the mind: that of the body evacuates the ſenſible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements; that of the mind the inſenſible rather, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe of the heart and brain, where the mind is ſeated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>An exceſſive reſt of the mind does more obſtruct perſpiration, than that of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>The exerciſes of the mind which moſt conduce to the cheering up of the ſpirits, are anger, ſudden joy, fear, and ſorrow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>Mens bodies reſting in bed, and agitated with a vehement motion of the mind, for the moſt part become more faint,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:102101:75"/>and leſs ponderous, than if there be a tranquillity of mind, with a violent motion of the body, as it happens at Tennice, or any game at Ball.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>By immoderate exerciſe the excrements of the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond concoction are for the moſt part diſpers'd through the compaſs of the whole body, and therefore the belly is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: yet are the bodies made lighter, becauſe the inſenſible evacuation is much greater than the excretion of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible excrements made by the belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>Violent exerciſe of mind and body renders bodies of lighter weight, haſtens old age, and threatens untimely death: for, according to the Philoſopher,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:102101:76"/>thoſe perſons that are exercis'd dye ſooner than ſuch as are not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>Violent exerciſe takes off from a body fill'd with meat or crude humours a leſs than uſual weight of the ſenſible excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; of the inſenſible, almoſt nothing at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>By exerciſe the body per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires leſs, by ſleep, more, and the belly is more looſned.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>Frictions and cupping-glaſſes, in bodies full of crudities, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>Then is exerciſe moſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; when, after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating of the firſt and ſecond concoction, the body is reduc'd twice in a day, before meat, to its uſual weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:102101:76"/>
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>Swimming immediately after violent exerciſe, is hurtful; for it very much obſtructs perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>Violent exerciſe in a place where the wind blows is hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>From the wind proceeds a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of reſpiration, from the motion, acrimony.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>Riding relates more to the perſpirable matter of the parts of the Body from the waſte up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, than downwards: but in riding the amble is the moſt wholſom, the trot the moſt unwholſom pace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>Waftage in Sedan or Horſe-litter, as alſo going by water,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:102101:77"/>does not ſo much diſpoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to due perſpiration, as walking.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>The motion of a Boat and Litter, if it be continu'd long, is moſt wholſom; for then on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it does wonderfully diſpoſe the body to due perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>Riding in a Coach or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot is the moſt violent of any way: for it does not only cauſe the unconcocted perſpirable matter to exhale out of the body, but alſo offends the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid parts of the body, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the Reins.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>Leaping does at firſt attract the ſtrength inwards, then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuouſly forces it to the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts, and with a certain violence expells the concocted
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:102101:77"/>matter, together with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concocted</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>The exerciſe of the Top, conſiſting of moderate and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent motion, to wit walking and the agitation of the Arms, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes perſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>Moderate dancing, without any capering or jumping, comes near the commendation of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate walking; for it moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expels the concocted perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable matter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:102101:78"/>
               <head>APHORISMS <hi>Added by the Author.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>WHen there is a defect of perſpiration in ſound bodies, it is remedy'd by exerciſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>By immoderate exerciſe the Fibres are hardned, whence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes old age, which is an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal hardneſs of the Fibers: this hardneſs, by condenſating the paſſages obſtructs the heat; ſoftneſs, by keeping them open, cauſes length of life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>He who would have a youthful face long, let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſweating, or perſpiring too much through heat.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:102101:78"/>
            <head>OF VENERY.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT.</hi> VI.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>Aphoriſm I.</head>
                  <p>TOO great abſtinence from Venery, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate uſe of it obſtruct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration; but the immoderate uſe of it does more obſtruct it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>After immoderate coition, the fourth part of the uſual per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration is commonly obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in moſt perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:102101:79"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>The miſchiefs occaſion'd by immoderate Coition do medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately depend on the hindrance of Perſpiration, immediately on the hurt done to the concoctive faculties.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>We find that Coition hath done good, if after the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſleep, there be no weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs felt, nor any alteration be made of the body, as to Gravity or Levity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>The continual thoughts of venereous perſons do ſometimes make their bodies heavier, ſometimes lighter; heavier, if they give way to them upon a full Stomach; lighter, if upon an empty one.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>After immoderate Coition
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:102101:79"/>with a woman whom a man had long deſir'd to enjoy, wearineſs is not preſently felt: for the ſatisfaction of the mind does then promote the Perſpiration of the heart, and augments its ſtrength; whence it comes, that, in ſuch a perſon, what is loſt is the ſooner recruited.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>If thoſe perſons who have a great inclination to Venery, do forbear the exerciſe of it, there preſently follows an agility of body, becauſe ſuch perſpire ſo much the better.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Immoderate coition oce ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Perſpiration of Crudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which afterwards cauſes a Chilneſs over the whole body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>Theſe are the ſigns that coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath not been hurtful;
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:102101:80"/>Urine equally concocted as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; Agility of body; a more eaſy Reſpiration, and the ſame weight of the body ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing; yet with an obſervance of the ſame diet, as to quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and quality.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>The preſent inconvenience of immoderate Coition is the Refrigeration of the Stomach; the conſequent to that obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſpiration; whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed Palpitations in the eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brows, and Joints, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the principal mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>Coition in the Summer is more hurtful than at other times, not by reaſon of the greater Perſpiration of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but becauſe the concoction being leſs, that which is loſt
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:102101:80"/>is with greater difficulty recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>In the act of Venery there is much crude matter perſpir'd, and if it continue long, the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities are transfer'd from the centre, to the Circumference of the body, obſtructions enſue, and thereupon the belly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes coſtive</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>The greater Propenſion a man has to the act of Venery, the leſs hurtful is the immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate exerciſe of it to him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>The detriment of immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Coition is particularly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd after the ſubſequent ſleep: for then it is found, by ſtatical Experiments, that the Perſpiration was obſtructed, and the meat ill-digeſted, as
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:102101:81"/>alſo that the Stomach was much prejudic'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>Coition is commonly hurtful to the firſt concoction, firſt by repreſſing the forwardneſs of Perſpiration, afterwards by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the meat into a crude quality.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>He who uſes Coition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Emiſſion of ſeed, is ſo much the leſs weakened. But if he again uſe the ſame exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the next day, and emit what had been prepar'd the day before, he is ſo much the leſs weakened.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>They, who, in the time of Coition, purpoſely forbear the Emiſſion of ſeed, are apt to be troubled with a ſwelling of the teſticles: for the ſeed is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:102101:81"/>
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>Immoderate Coition, next to the Stomach, is prejudicial to the eyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>Immoderate Coition is hurtful to the ſight, becauſe it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws a very great plenty of ſpirits from the eyes, thence comes it that the Tunicles of the eyes become very hard and wrinkled, and the paſſages leſs pervious.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>The Fibres of the Tunicles of the Eyes become more opake upon the diminution of perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; thence the ſight is made through very ſmall ſpaces, ſuch as are thoſe in lattices. Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles unite the objects into a point, that they may be diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen through one ſingle ſpace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:102101:82"/>
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>By immoderate Coition, the natural heat is diminiſh'd, by the diminution of the heat, there comes a diminution of the Perſpiration; from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of the Perſpiration proceed Flatulency and Palpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>Immoderate Coition requires little meat, and that of good nutriment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>Coition heats the liver and reins, becauſe the excited heat exhales not: but it cools the ſtomach, the brain, and the heart, becauſe it is wholly excited through the more open paſſages, and the innate heat is thereupon in ſome part diſſolved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>Hence it comes, that immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:102101:82"/>coition cauſes choler in the Liver; a painful aking in the Reins; a crude humour in the ſtomach; a catarrhe in the Brain; and palpitation and a ſyncope in the heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>If the meat a man eats after immoderate coition beget flatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, as Oyſters, and new wine, they are pernicious; for they hinder the body from being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to its uſual weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>Coition is more hurtful to lean perſons, becauſe they are the more heated, and the more refrigerated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>Immoderate coition does im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately make the body more light, though it afterwards ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct perſpiration; for it is a vehement motion of the body
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:102101:83"/>and mind; of the body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a concuſſion of all the members; of the mind, becauſe that which makes a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction between the body and the mind is looſned, to wit, the vital ſpirit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>If a diſturbance in ſleeping ſucceeds coition, the ſubſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made by coition is greater, than the addition of the vital ſpirit made by ſleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>After the immoderate uſe of Venery, ſleep attracts crudities to the heart; the conſequences whereof are a languiſhing faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, an obſtruction of perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and augmentation of weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>Old men by the uſe of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate coition become more
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:102101:83"/>ponderous and more cold; but young men more light, and more hot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>Coition, in young men, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborates the Animal, vital, and natural heat; it drives out the Animal heat by motion, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites the ſluggiſh natural heat by the evacuation of that which is ſuperfluous, and the vital, by alacrity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>More plentiful feeding than is uſual to a man, after immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate coition would deſtroy him, if there enſu'd not ſome corruption of the meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>When a man is to uſe coition, he ſhould eat little or nothing; when he is to eat, he ſhould be very moderate in coition, or quite forbear it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:102101:84"/>
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>If after exceſſive coition there be no wearineſs felt, it is an ill ſign. The caſe is the ſame as happens in diſtracted perſons by the inflamed ſpirits, which by drying in a ſhort ſpace corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate the nerves and tendons, but a while after the generation of the ſpirits is abated, and the ſtrength is immediately remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>APHORISMS <hi>Added by the Author.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>COition excited by nature is good; excited by the mind is hurtful to the mind and memory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:102101:84"/>
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>In weak perſons the weight of the body is augmented by coition; becauſe they perſpire the leſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVII.</head>
                  <p>Inſatiable coition obſtructs perſpiration, becauſe it abates the ſtrength; whence the body becomes more ponderous, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a looſneſs of the belly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>Immoderate coition occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a great detriment, by calefaction and exſiccation: but if the heat be recruited by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible perſpiration, and the drought by aliment, none at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIX.</head>
                  <p>The agitation of the body in coition, like that of Dogs, does, more hurt than the emiſſion of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:102101:85"/>the ſeed; for the latter wearies only the internal parts; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tires all the nerves and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XL.</head>
                  <p>The uſe of coition after meat, and ſtanding, is hurtful; after meat, it diverts the office of the entrails; ſtanding, it diverts the muſcles, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes their beneficial perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLI.</head>
                  <p>After motion, coition is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome; after meat, not ſo much; after ſleep, it is moſt wholeſome of all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLII.</head>
                  <p>Coition heats the liver, and cools the ſtomach; from the ſtomach proceeds a crude moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; from the liver, choler; whence proceeds that kind of choler which is called
<hi>Porracea,</hi>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:102101:85"/>being of a colour reſembling that of a Leek. The remedy is, a ſlender diet, and a free per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:102101:86"/>
            <head>OF THE AFFECTIONS OF THE MIND.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT.</hi> VII.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>Aphoriſm I.</head>
                  <p>AMongſt the affections of the mind, Anger and alacrity render mens bodies lighter; Fear and Sadneſs, more ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; And the reſt of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons operate anſwerably to their participation of theſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:102101:86"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>In Grief and Fear that which is lighter perſpires, but what is more ponderous is left behind; in Gladneſs and Anger there is a perſpiration of both.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Hence it comes to paſs that ſuch as are ſubject to Fear and Grief are apt to be troubled with obſtructions, hardneſs of the parts, and hypochondriacal affections.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Such as are angry or joyful feel no wearineſs in travelling; for their bodies eaſily perſpire the groſs matter; which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens not, when they are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with grief, or fear.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>The ponderous part of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable matter, being more than uſually retain'd in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:102101:87"/>diſpoſes a man to ſadneſs and fear; but the light part diſpoſes him to gladneſs and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Nothing contributes more to freedom of reſpiration, than ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and conſolation of mind.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>By ſadneſs and fear the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers moſt full of moiſture are eaſily indurated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Grief and fear obſtruct the perſpiration of the groſs perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable excrements; and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of perſpiration, from what cauſe ſoever it proceeds, cauſes grief and fear.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>Grief, if it continue long, brings a coldneſs on the fleſh; for it hinders the exhalation of
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:102101:87"/>the groſs portion of the perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>Hence it comes, that that feaver which a man falls into after much grief diſcovers it ſelf in cold ſweats, and thoſe many times mortal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>The acrimony of the perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable matter which is retain'd by the means of grief, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently taken off by alacrity: for pleaſant humours are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diffus'd through the body, and thereupon ponderoſity and acrimony are taken off from it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>Anger and hope take away fear, and joy taketh away ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: for a paſſion of the mind is overcome, not by Medicines, but by ſome contrary paſſion: for contraries are under the ſame genus.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:102101:88"/>
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>It does not imply any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, to affirm, that the retention of the perſpirable matter in melancholy perſons, is cold and acrimonious, or hot: ſuch are the Livers of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropical perſons who are in Feavers; to wit, they are cold in reſpect of the natural heat, and hot, in reſpect of the adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>Diſeaſes proceeding from me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy and a cloſe muddy air, agree in this, that they are immediately occaſion'd by the groſſneſs of the perſpirable matter which is retain'd: For grief does intrinſecally obſtruct the excretion of the groſs mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the muddy air does it extrinſecally.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:102101:88"/>
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>They who carry grief along with them to their beds, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire ſo much the leſs that night; and the next day their bodies continue more than uſually ponderous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>In venereous meditations, the groſs part of the perſpirable excrements, is, with grief re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd; which part, upon the evaporation of the ſubtile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes yet more groſs and more cold: If this be pent up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, it cauſes an almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible coldneſs in the head, and a hardly curable palpitation in the heart, or other members.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>Melancholy is two ways o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, either by a free per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, or ſome continual ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the mind.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:102101:89"/>
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>If mens bodies become lighter after grief than after joy, it muſt of neceſſity happen either by reaſon of a leſs quantity of meat, or by that of their more tranſpirable quality.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>The conſolation of the mind, from whatſoever cauſe it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, opens the paſſages, and very much promotes perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>'f after anger there immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atey enſue ſome conſolation of the mind; or the contrary hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, mens bodies, allowing an equal proportion of aliment, are lighter the next day, than they would be if only anger or joy had continu'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>As there is a ſudden period
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:102101:89"/>put to ſome great pleaſure by a ſmall evacuation of ſeed: ſo all other immoderate affections of the mind may be abated and taken off, by ſome evacuation of the perſpirable matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>Fear and grief, as we find by ſtatical experiments, are taken off by the evacuation of the groſs perſpirable excrements; anger and alacrity, by that of the tenuious.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>If any one find himſelf in a merry jocund humour, without any cauſe, it proceeds from a greater freedom of perſpiration, and his body will be found
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he next day of leſs weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>Moderate joy inſenſibly eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuates what is ſuperfluous; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate joy, both what is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:102101:90"/>and what is bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>Moderate joy aſſiſts the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctive faculties; for nature, not being burthen'd with that which is ſuperfluous, does much better perform her functions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>Unexpected joy is more hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than that which is look'd for: For it does not only excite the evacuation of the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the third concoction, but alſo the exhalation of the vital ſpirits; but the expected joy promotes only that of the excrements.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>Joy and anger take off from the body what makes it more ponderous, and what renders it more light: Grief and fear take away only what makes it
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:102101:90"/>more light, but what makes it more ponderous is left behind.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>A continual gladneſs for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daies together hinders ſleep, and renders a man weaker.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>If any one, after moderate joy finds himſelf lighter, it does not proceed principally from the evacuation of the whole body, but from that of the heart and brain, whence what is evacuated is leaſt of all, as to quantity, and greateſt, as to vertue.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe aliments, which open and facilitate perſpiration, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce joy, thoſe that obſtruct it, grief.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>Parſley, and other aliments that are opening, induce joy;
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:102101:91"/>Pulſe, fat meat, and other things which incraſſate, and preſently fill the cavities of the paſſages, cauſe grief.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>If the cavities of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages be evacuated, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards preſently fill'd, it was rightly ſaid of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> that evil paſſions of the mind are generated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>To thoſe who are ſubject to anger, immoderate exerciſe is very hurtful; for their paſſages are immediately empty'd, and with much violence are fill'd up again. Whence it came that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> forbad Cholerick perſons to uſe frictions, and wraſtling.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>In a perſon who uſes no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of body or mind, the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:102101:91"/>paſſages are not empty'd, nor are there any evil paſſions of the mind contracted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>A body lying all along does perſpire more, and becomes of leſs weight, if the mind be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently active, than if the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy were in a very ſwift motion, and the mind were idle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>The ſhifting of the body from one place to another makes a longer alteration of the body, than of the mind it ſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVII.</head>
                  <p>The paſſions of the mind are concern'd about the internal ſubject, which rather moves, than is moved: inaſmuch as it is leaſt, as to quantity, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, as to Vertue, like the ſperm of man, and by the diſpoſal there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:102101:92"/>in ſeveral manners is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigine of Perſpiration, or Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deroſity, and Lightneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXVIII</head>
                  <p>Thoſe bodies which perſpire more than uſually, not occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd by any motion of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but through ſome vehement agitation of the mind, are with greater difficulty reduc'd to their uſual and healthy Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XXXIX.</head>
                  <p>An immoderate affection of the mind is more hurtful, than an immoderate motion of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XL.</head>
                  <p>The body would pine away, and be deſtroy'd through idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, were it not for the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the mind; but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary cannot be affirm'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLI.</head>
                  <p>A vehement motion of the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:102101:92"/>mind differs from a vehement motion of the body; the latter is taken off by reſt and ſleep; the former by neither reſt nor ſleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLII.</head>
                  <p>Let thoſe forbear gaming whoſe thoughts are altogether upon winning; becauſe if they always have good fortune, out of exceſſive joy, they will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſleep in the night, and, in time, will find the want of the exhalation of the concocted perſpirable matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIII.</head>
                  <p>A moderate victory is more wholſome than a glorious one.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLIV.</head>
                  <p>Study is longer endur'd in a viciſſitude of the affections of the mind, than if it be without affection, or without any change of affections; for Perſpiration
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:102101:93"/>becomes more moderate, and more wholſome.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLV.</head>
                  <p>Study, without any affection, hardly endures an hour; with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one affection, hardly four hours; with viciſſitude of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as at Dice, at which kind of gaming men feel, one while, the joy for winning, another, ſadneſs for loſing, it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue night and day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVI.</head>
                  <p>In all Study continual ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs diſturbs the good conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the heart, and exceſs of gladneſs hinders ſleep; for every exceſs is deſtructive to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVII.</head>
                  <p>They who are ſometimes merry, ſometimes ſad, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times angry, ſometimes timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, have a more healthful
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:102101:93"/>perſpiration, than they who continue in one and the ſame, though that a conſtantly-good affection.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XLVIII.</head>
                  <p>Gladneſs makes the Diaſtole and the Syſtole more eaſy; grief and ſadneſs render them more difficult.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:102101:94"/>
            <head>TO THE STATICOMASTIX.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT.</hi> VIII.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                  <head>Aphoriſm I.</head>
                  <p>THE <hi>Staticomaſtix,</hi> while he attributes the cure of diſeaſes to the poſition of the Heavens, Paralogizes, by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning a more common cauſe than he needed to have done.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>The fool firſt denies, yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards admits Staticks or Ponderation, affirming, that there is a diverſity of weight
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:102101:94"/>in a guilty perſon, and an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. In like manner, he firſt denies that the ſpirits of Swine are light; and afterwards he would have their getting up to any place to proceed from the lightneſs of their ſpirits.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>He who is experienc'd in Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, knows the weight of the excrements, though he neither ſee them, nor weigh them. He weighs the body before, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, after all evacuation; what is deficient is their weight: And ſo 'tis no unſeemly thing to weigh the excrements, as the Trifler affirms.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>No Student in Phyſick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the fool himſelf, but knows, that the vital faculty is diffus'd into the Arteries, and the animal into the nerves,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:102101:95"/>by raies, and not by ſpirits; as he imagines.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>The fool thinks that light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as to the ballance, in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bodies, proceeds from the plenty of ſpirits; it ſeems he never knew, that dead bodies are lighter than the living, and that living bodies, after coition, weigh leſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>He belies the Author, affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the faculty of moving bodies upwards is no other than the ſpirits themſelves; whereas the Author affirms, that the ſpirits are inanimate, and that they gravitate more than air.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>He is out again, when he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that mens bodies are cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the night time; therefore
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:102101:95"/>they perſpire little, or nothing. Nor did he ever obſerve, that the pulſe and nocturnal perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration are ſigns of a more hot body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>The fool thinks that living bodies are lighter than the dead; never having taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that Butchers, Fiſh-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and ſuch as deal in Swine, when they ſell the living, make a deduction of ten pounds in the hundred weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>The extravagant man never thinks of the difference there is between ones being light, if weigh'd in the ballance, and the ſame perſon's feeling himſelf lighter. A man may be ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his being very ponderous, and yet be lighter in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:102101:96"/>
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>We know the weight of the body by meaſure, not by imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as our inconſiderate fool does, who imagines that flegm is more ponderous than blood, yet never obſerv'd, that the former does ſwim on the top; and that by reaſon of flegm the body is not really, but is felt of greater weight. But why? becauſe it obſtructs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>He charges the Author with a falſity in making him affirm that inſenſible perſpiration is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flation of the fleſh, when he affirms no ſuch thing. In the winter-time, there are about ſixty ounces perſpir'd in the ſpace of one day with eaſe; if that perſpiration were of fleſh, a man's body would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:102101:96"/>
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Galen</hi> made no mention of <hi>Statick</hi> Medicine, therefore 'tis a vain ſcience. He is doubly miſtaken; firſt, becauſe he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read his ſix Books <hi>De Tuenda, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, it does not follow, <hi>Galen</hi> ſaid nothing of it, therefore it is vain: we have found out many inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and thoſe not contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which were not known be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our times.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>The famous Author of the Commentary on the XII. of the firſt Section of Aphoriſms, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, that the meat is propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionated to the difflation, and Com. XV. that there is a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er difflation in the winter-time, therefore it is requiſite there ſhould be more meat eaten: it is therefore requiſite the weight
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:102101:97"/>ſhould be known; all which the trifling Staticomaſtix de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>The fool, making no experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments himſelf, denies thoſe things, that others have found true by experience. He boldly adds this aſſertion; If thirty ſix ounces be perſpir'd in the ſpace of one night, there will be thirty two of fleſh, and four of excrements.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>The trifling Anſwerer puts the lie on all Authors, affirming that the ſpirits are more tenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than the Air. Are they not made of the blood and Air? Does not the Air paſs through the whole body? but the ſpirits remain inclos'd in Veſſels.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:102101:97"/>
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>He affirms that a plentiful perſpiration does not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, from the body, one ounce of its weight. There's no temerity deſerves greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, than ſuch a man's, as makes no account of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yet oppoſes experience. We have found it certainly true, that in the ſpace of a night, the body weighs leſs by three pound, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter coition, mens bodies are lighter, as to the Ballance. Therefore the fool is charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with a lie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>He affirms, that, after an immoderate purgation of the termes, bodies are more pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous, after an extraordinary retention of them, more light. A fatal errour to the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:102101:98"/>man, who does not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, between being hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, in reference to the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and one's feeling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf heavy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What literal faults there may be, the intelligent Reader will eaſily find, and Correct.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102101:98"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
